<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian consolations taught from five heads in religion I. Faith. II. Hope. III. The Holy Spirit. IV. Prayer. V. The Sacraments. Written by a learned prelate.</title>
            <author>Learned prelate.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 122 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3943A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898041</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898041</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79541)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2552:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian consolations taught from five heads in religion I. Faith. II. Hope. III. The Holy Spirit. IV. Prayer. V. The Sacraments. Written by a learned prelate.</title>
                  <author>Learned prelate.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 219, [3] p., plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Royston, bookseller to his most excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"I. Faith" to "IV. Prayer" are connected by a complex system of brackets.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Conſolations</hi> Taught from FIVE HEADS IN RELIGION.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>Hope.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>The Holy Spirit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. <hi>The Sacraments.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Written by a Learned PRELATE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 40.1, 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, ſaith your God:</p>
               <p>Speak ye comfortably to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and cry unto her, that her warfare is accompliſhed, that her iniquity is pardoned —</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to his moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135920:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135920:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THIS Manual of <hi>Chriſtian Conſolations</hi> derived from <hi>Five</hi> Heads of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in Religion, was written by a late R. Prelate of our Church, and is now Printed according to his own Copy.</p>
            <p>The Papers were preſented by him to a Perſon of Honour, for whoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate uſe they were deſigned: But, as the Nobleſt Spirits are moſt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative, that Noble and Religious La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was pleaſed to impart them for the good alſo of others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135920:3"/>We read in the Evangeliſts how that the Holy <hi>Jeſus, who went about doing good</hi> (that's the ſhort, but full, Character which<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 10.38.</note> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> gives of him) did by a Miracle of Mercy bleſs <hi>five Loaves</hi> to the feeding of a very great multitude. And may the ſame Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Goodneſs bleſs and proſper whatſoever Spiritual good is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe <hi>Five Helps</hi> and <hi>Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for a Chriſtian's Comfort,</hi> to the refreſhing and ſtrengthening of ſuch Souls as truly hunger and thirſt after God. May the ſerious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Readers <hi>taſte and ſee how good the Lord is,</hi> that <hi>his Loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is better than Life,</hi> and that the <hi>Light of his Countenance,</hi> the ſenſe of his favour, is infinitely more Heart-cheering, and brings with it a truer and larger ſatisfaction than the encreaſe of <hi>Corn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:135920:3"/>
               <hi>and Wine, and Oil</hi> doth to the men of this world, who only or chiefly <hi>mind Earthly things,</hi> and unwiſely place their felicity in the fading and empty enjoyments of this preſent life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is good</hi> then <hi>that a man ſhould both hope and quietly wait for the Salvation of the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> for <hi>he is good to them that wait for him, to the Soul that ſeeketh him.</hi> He who is the God of Love, and even<note n="*" place="margin">1 Jo. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Love</hi> it ſelf; He who is the ever-flowing Fountain of Goodneſs, will not fail to <hi>fill the hungry with good things.</hi> Such a Chriſtian hath meat to eat which the world knows not of; he feeds on the <hi>hidden Manna:</hi> he hath (as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid of S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe) occultum os in corde ejus,</hi> and with this he doth <hi>ſapida gaudia de pane Dei ruminare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135920:4"/>The Father of the World, who <hi>openeth his hand, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieth the deſire of every living thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> giving to all <hi>their meat in due ſeaſon;</hi> he is as ready <hi>to fulfil the deſire of them that fear him;</hi> he will give <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> and no good thing will he withhold from them that <hi>walk uprightly.</hi> And here from the character and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of the Perſons [<hi>them that fear him,</hi> and <hi>them that walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly</hi>] it highly concerns us to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and to lay it to heart, That a Sincere deſire and Serious endeavour <hi>to fear God</hi> and <hi>walk uprightly</hi> is a neceſſary and indiſpenſable Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to qualifie and make us meet for the receiving of the beſt of Divine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and bleſſings. We muſt firſt <hi>walk in the fear of the Lord,</hi> if we would <hi>walk in the Comfort of the
<pb facs="tcp:135920:4"/>
Holy Ghoſt;</hi> as theſe two are ſet together in <hi>Acts 9.31.</hi> If we would have the Spirit to be our <hi>Comforter,</hi> we muſt follow the Spirit as our Guide and <hi>Counſellor.</hi> If we would find <hi>reſt unto our Souls,</hi> we muſt <hi>take Chriſt's yoke upon us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11.</note> the yoke of his Precepts, which are all holy, and juſt, and good. A state of inward Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and true Tranquillity of Spirit can never be ſecured and preſerved, but by a continued care to walk before God in a faithful obedience to his Will in all things.</p>
            <p>For <hi>there is no peace to the wicked;</hi> as is<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 48. 22. Chap. 57. 21.</note> twice expreſt by the noble Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> But <hi>Great peace have they that love thy Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.165.</note> ſaith the Royal <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> the man after God's own heart, who
<pb facs="tcp:135920:5"/>
herein ſpake his own experience; and elſewhere,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note> 
               <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, for the end of that man is peace.</hi> While he lives, he lives in peace, his Soul dwells at eaſe; he feels an unſpeakable joy and pleaſure within, upon the ſenſe of his doing his duty, and being faithful in obedience to his Lord and Maſter in Heaven. And when he dies, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts in peace, and ſhall<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 57.</note> 
               <hi>enter into peace,</hi> and<note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> into <hi>the joy</hi> of his Lord. Here he <hi>taſtes</hi> how ſweet the Lord is, but there he ſhall be <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied with the plenty of God's Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> 
               <hi>and made to drink of the River of his pleaſures. The meek ſhall eat and be ſatisfied; and their heart ſhall live for ever.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> And ſo full and compleat ſhall be their joy and ſatisfaction,
<pb facs="tcp:135920:5"/>
that <hi>they ſhall neither hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger nor thirſt any more;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 7.</note> 
               <hi>for the Lamb ſhall feed them, and ſhall lead them unto living Fountains of waters; and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes.</hi> This is the happy Portion of thoſe Souls, who have the Lord for their God, with whom there is fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures moſt pure and permanent for evermore.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:135920:6"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Introduction.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I. Of Faith.</label>
That <hi>Faith</hi> is the Ground and Foundation of a Chriſtian's Comfort. Several doubts and ſcruples about Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, anſwered. <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II. Of Hope.</label>
That a Chriſtian's Comfort flows from the Grace of <hi>Hope.</hi> The object of Hope is, <hi>1.</hi> That which is Good.
<pb facs="tcp:135920:6"/>
                  <hi>2.</hi> A Good abſent. <hi>3.</hi> Though abſent, yet poſſible; and that for Three Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. <hi>4.</hi> Though poſſible, yet diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult. An account of two ſorts of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, with particular encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt them. <hi>Pag. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III. Of the Holy Spirit.</label>
How a Chriſtian's Comforts flow from the Inhabitation and Teſtimony of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> as alſo from the Sanctification of the Spirit unto all Obedience, and the fruits of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. <hi>Pag. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IV. Of Prayer.</label>
                  <hi>Prayer</hi> is the great Inſtrument of a Chriſtian's Comfort. Concerning
<pb facs="tcp:135920:7"/>
                  <hi>Prayer</hi> three things to be conſidered: <hi>I.</hi> The Subſtance or Matter of Prayer, in three Heads. <hi>1.</hi> Thanksgivings. <hi>2.</hi> Supplications. <hi>3.</hi> Interceſſions. <hi>II.</hi> The Qualification of them that Pray. <hi>III.</hi> The fitneſs of Time for Prayer. <hi>Pag. 99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. V. Of the Sacraments.</label>
How the <hi>Sacraments</hi> miniſter to a Chriſtian's Comfort. A general Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Five Reaſons why God ordained Two <hi>Sacraments</hi> under the Goſpel. What Comforts flow from the Grace of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> What Comforts flow from the <hi>Lord's Supper. Pag. 155.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135920:7"/>
            <head>Chriſtian Conſolations taught from five Heads in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <p>THE work of the Miniſtry conſiſts in two things; in Threatnings or Comforts: The firſt is uſeful for the greateſt part of Chriſtians, who are led by the Spirit of bondage, and fear to do evil, becauſe of wrath to come; which grows out of love to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The ſecond is fit for the beſt Chriſtians, that are led by the
<pb facs="tcp:135920:8"/>
Spirit of love; who endeavour to do righteouſneſs, becauſe they love righteouſneſs, and to be like unto God, who, they know, is only good (which grows out of the ſpirit of adoption) and obey as ſons and daughters, and not as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour and his Apoſtles inſiſt ſometimes upon the former way, threatning the impenitent, yet qualifying it with tidings of peace, if they return and amend their lives. For <hi>ſharpneſs</hi> muſt be applied, <hi>according to the power which the Lord hath given for edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and not for deſtruction,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10. The ſame Apoſtle propounds both in the former Epiſtle, Chap. 4. Verſe 21. <hi>Shall I come unto you with a rod? or in love, and in the ſpirit of meekneſs?</hi> Which latter is moſt ſuitable to
<pb facs="tcp:135920:8"/>
the Goſpel, to proclaim <hi>peace on earth, and good will towards men.</hi> And when <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> would have had fire to come down from Heaven upon the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> Chriſt reproved them, ſaying, <hi>The Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them,</hi> Luke 9.56. and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.9. <hi>God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to obtain ſalvation by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſurely there is cauſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a cluſter of conſolation againſt a few grains of terror; 1. Becauſe we are all concluded under ſin, and the guilt is ever preſent unto us. 2. Becauſe of the weakneſs of the Graces that are in us: not that they are weak, but that humane corruption is mixt with them. 3. Becauſe of the ſtrength and manifoldneſs of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. 4. Becauſe we are to be
<pb facs="tcp:135920:9"/>
exerciſed with the ſufferance of the Croſs, and we are infirm to bear it. Laſtly, Becauſe little is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to us at the preſent of that Reward we look for; leaſt of all is any ſhare of it preſent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes. Foraſmuch then as there are ſo many in-draughts that break into our heart, to make us ſick of ſorrow and fear, let us ſeek comfort from God, who hath left no diſeaſe without a remedy to cure it, <hi>who healeth all thy diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Pſalm</hi> 103.3. I ſay it is to be ſought from God, leſt we light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that <hi>tell falſe dreams, and comfort in vain, Zach.</hi> 10.2. The right place for it muſt be the Word of God, as it is <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>That we through patience, and comfort of the Scripture might have hope.</hi> Which comfort ſcatter'd up and down in that Holy Book, and not caſt all into a lump together, by
<pb facs="tcp:135920:9"/>
ſearching it diligently, we may draw our Conſolation out of five things, <hi>Faith, Hope, The in-dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Spirit, Prayer, and the Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Coronata Fides</p>
                  <p>Dux viae</p>
                  <p>prudens simplicitas</p>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:135920:11"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135920:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> That <hi>Faith</hi> is the Ground and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a Chriſtian's Comfort. Several doubts and ſcruples about believing, anſwered.</head>
               <p>FAITH is the Root of all bleſſings. Believe, and you ſhall be ſaved: Believe, and you muſt needs be ſanctified: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and you cannot chuſe but be comforted: Believe that God is true in all his promiſes, and you are the ſeed of faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſhall inherit the promiſes made to <hi>Abraham.</hi> Believe that you are Chriſts, and Chriſt is yours; and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135920:12"/>
then you are ſure that none can pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, whom the Father hath given to him. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 8.1. And as <hi>Martha</hi> ſaid, <hi>Lord, if thou hadſt been here, my brother had not died, Jo.</hi> 11.21. So let all ſay that groan, and pine away in ſorrow, Lord, if thou hadſt been here, if thou hadſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to my ſoul in thy goodneſs, I had not fainted in my trouble. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretells, Chap. 61.3. that it ſhould be Chriſts office <hi>to give the oil of joy for mourning, and the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> For St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they that follow Chriſt, are cloathed <hi>in white garments,</hi> in garments of joy, in the livery of gladneſs. <hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribing the provident Miſtreſs of a Family, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.21. ſays, <hi>She is not afraid of the ſnow for her houſhold, for all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135920:12"/>
her houſhold are cloathed with ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let:</hi> So the houſhold of Chriſt are not afraid of froſt and ſnow, nor of any bitter blaſt, they have put on the garment of dependence on Chriſt, which protects them, and do reſolve never to put off their privy-coat of confidence in their Saviour. With this did Chriſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the poor woman, being under confuſion, who had ſecretly toucht the hem of his garment, <hi>Be of comfort, thy Faith hath made thee whole, Matth.</hi> 9.22.</p>
               <p>The firſt time that the word <hi>[Comfort]</hi> is found in Scripture, is <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.29. upon the birth of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah;</hi> his Father ſays, <hi>This Son ſhall Comfort us:</hi> ſo when God did give Chriſt to be made man, he did as it were ſay unto us, This Son ſhall Comfort you, for his name is <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>he ſhall ſave his people from their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135920:13"/>
ſins.</hi> He that gave us him, hath given us all things with him. As it is true to ſay, that <hi>Matthew</hi> left all to follow Chriſt, ſo it is as true, that he got all that can be wiſht by following him.</p>
               <p>It is the <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> (let me uſe that word) to turn all things into good and precious Ore. It is <hi>Abraham's</hi> Country in a ſtrange land: <hi>Jacob's</hi> wages when <hi>Laban</hi> defrauded him: <hi>Moſes</hi>'s ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, when he refuſed to be the ſon in law of <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> daughter: <hi>Rahab's</hi> ſecurity, when all <hi>Jericho</hi> beſide did periſh: <hi>David's</hi> reſcue, when there was but a ſtep between him and death: The power of the Apoſtles to be able to caſt out De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils: <hi>Mary Magdalen's</hi> ſweet oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to take away the ill ſavour of her ſins. Plead therefore with the Oratory of <hi>Faith,</hi> and ſay, Lord,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135920:13"/>
                  <q>I have no life but in thee, I have no joy but in thee, no ſalvation but in thee: but I have all theſe in thee; and then how can my Soul refuſe to be Comforted?</q>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome will ſay perhaps, <hi>Faith</hi> is a powerful Comforter: but I, poor wretch, had need to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted concerning my <hi>Faith.</hi> I find the pulſe of it weak, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it intermits, as if it beat not at all. Methinks I am not drawn near to Chriſt, or that I am ſo far off, that I cannot embrace him. Some ſuch infirmity may ſeem to have been in the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>I have ſent Timotheus to eſtabliſh you, and to comfort you concerning your Faith,</hi> 1 Epiſt. Chap. 3. Ver. 2.</p>
               <p>Now to turn this water into wine, and the trembling of this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135920:14"/>
into peace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt, conceive as if theſe queſtions were put to you; Do you often accuſe your ſelf of a weak Faith in ſecret unto God? I like it for a good ſymptome; for an hypocrite doth not uſe to accuſe himſelf. And do you bewail your want to the Lord, becauſe you would have it better ſupplied? that's a good ſign too, for it is the ſame as to thirſt for the living God. They that have not the gift of <hi>Faith,</hi> do not miſs it: but they that have it, though but in a little, do inſatiably deſire the increaſe of it.</p>
               <p>But do you find that the more you put forward to come to Chriſt, the more you are put back by doubts and temptations? It is right the reſemblance of him that was ſick of the palſie, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.4. fain
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135920:14"/>
he would have been brought to Chriſt, but could not come at him for the preſs. This preſs that ſtops you, are the ſnares of the world, vain imaginations, nay, perhaps humility, a broken heart, and a tender conſcience: Yet find out a way to come to your Saviour, though the throng be cumberſom. If there be no other way, untile the houſe, break down the roof to be brought unto him: call unto the Lord to diſſolve this houſe of clay, that thy Soul may ſee him clearly without all impediment.</p>
               <p>But, at the worſt of all, do you lie in a ſwoon as it were? do you think there is no life, no motion in your <hi>Faith?</hi> do you fear the light of grace is ſo eclipſed, that you have loſt all communion with Chriſt? Remember, and be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that you could not miſs Chriſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135920:15"/>
ſo much, unleſs Chriſt were in you. Becauſe God loves you, he ſeems to leave you; and withdraws out of the way for a time, becauſe he would be found; and makes you deſire to ſeek him, that you may hold him the ſurer to you when you enjoy him.</p>
               <p>A mother that hath conceiv'd, may think not long after, that ſhe perceives ſome tokens of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; in a while ſhe doubts of it again, and wiſheth ſome ſigns of better ſatisfaction: ſhe hangs long under many aſſays of fear and perſwaſion: at laſt ſhe finds the babe ſpring in her womb, and is utterly confirm'd. So it is with them in whom Chriſt is born anew, they have found the Lord, yet ſometime, as it is in the Canticles, <hi>He is behind the lattice,</hi> that we miſs him with a ſpiritual jealouſie,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135920:15"/>
and fall into many of theſe fits, as if he were quite departed. And in this ſtate of trepidation we muſt be exerciſed, that we may know, that holy fear and a troubled ſpirit are heavenly qualities that may conſiſt with <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet I have more to ask. Do you look dejectedly upon your <hi>Faith,</hi> becauſe you apprehend it is not full of life in the root, nor lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with fruit in Godly practice? Wo be to them that are not ſenſible of thoſe infirmities. It is one of the beſt leſſons in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Be strong in the grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> but it is one of the hardeſt. God gives a meaſure of <hi>Faith</hi> to all in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant that call upon him; but we have this gift in earthen veſſels, and taint it with the affections of our carnal mind. The beſt <hi>Faith</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:135920:16"/>
is weak, wavering, ſhort-ſighted, riſeth and falls like a tune in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. Therefore to encourage a perplexed mind, hearken to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 35.4. <hi>Say to them that are of a ſorrowful heart, be ſtrong, fear not.</hi> For though it be but an Infant-faith, it is a true Faith: as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant is a true man in the eſſence of a man, though not a man in growth; perfect in the real being, though not in the degrees, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we muſt ſtrive to grow up more and more. To prove the truth of it, believe all the Word of God, and it can be no wider: and for the ſoundneſs of it, believe in Chriſt, and look for ſalvation in him alone, then it is as legitimate and true born, as is the Faith of any Saint that is far more noble. A dim, or a blear-eye, that lookt upon the brazen Serpent, did procure a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for a wound, as much as a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135920:16"/>
clear and well-condition'd Eye. And a little Faith, caſting its weak beams upon Chriſt and his death, will go far. The quantity of a grain of Muſtard-ſeed hath warmth and vertue in it to ſpread abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If any Faith on earth had ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off all frailty, and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the joys of Heaven, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out caſting its eye aſide to the love of this world, I do not conceive how the body could ſubſiſt any longer here, but that the Soul in that extaſie would be diſſolved and fly away.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, as God ſees ſuch ſins in you, as you cannot ſee, ſo he ſees ſuch Graces in you as you cannot perceive. The charitable, to whom Chriſt ſpeaks when they are at his right hand, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch good things to be in them, as Chriſt did profeſs they had.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135920:17"/>
The <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> woman found no better in her ſelf than the vileneſs of a Dog, that waited for crums under the table, but Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends her for her great Faith. The <hi>Centurion, Matth.</hi> 8. ſaw nothing but unworthineſs in his perſon: but Chriſt gave him the praiſe above all thoſe to whom he had preacht in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Confeſs then, and be not aſhamed to ſay, Lord I believe, help my unbelief; and take conſolation, that water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprings ſhall flow out of a barren ground, which ſuſpected it ſelf to be parcht and dry. Though you ſee but little by your own light, it is becauſe it is put into the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn of humility. And let theſe be the conſolations of Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:135920:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That a Chriſtian's Comfort flows from the Grace of Hope. The object of Hope is, <hi>1.</hi> That which is Good. <hi>2.</hi> A Good abſent. <hi>3.</hi> Though abſent, yet poſſible; and that for three Reaſons. <hi>4.</hi> Though poſſible, yet difficult. An account of two ſorts of difficulties, with particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar encouragements againſt them.</head>
               <p>YET know that <hi>Faith</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver rides ſingle, but it carries <hi>Hope</hi> before it. <hi>Faith is the ſubſtance of things Hoped for, Heb.</hi> 11.1. No Scripture doth better contain them both in a little than <hi>Titus,</hi> Chap. 1. Verſe 1, 2. The Apoſtle ſays, That <hi>the Faith
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135920:18"/>
of Gods Elect,</hi> firſt, <hi>acknowledgeth the Truth.</hi> Secondly, That <hi>it is according to Godlineſs.</hi> Thirdly, It is <hi>in hope of Eternal life, which God that cannot lye, promiſed before the world began.</hi> When you ſee a weight of iron tied to a line, wound up on a wheel from the ground to the top of an houſe, remember it is like the heart of a ſinner, leaden and heavy, lying upon the ground, and wound up in this Text with the line of <hi>Hope</hi> to the top of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Heaven then is the expreſs and fair object of <hi>Hope,</hi> and God in his <hi>promiſe</hi> is the procurer. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> I ſay: For we do not grope for Heaven blind-fold; and fall upon it out of our own head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a warrant: but our aſſurance is incomparably the beſt that can be given, and in the beſt manners <hi>a Promiſe made before the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> that is, freely, unrequeſted,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135920:18"/>
when we could have no being to ask it: and made over to Chriſt the Mediator, that it ſhould be put into his hand to perform it to us. And it is unchangeable, as is all the truth of God: for <hi>he cannot lye,</hi> neither is there any ſhadow of change in him. What can we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire more? Carry this evidence along with you, and ſhew it to your ſelf upon every diſquietneſs and deep plunge of heart: and how can you chuſe but convince your ſelf, that your melancholy and diſtruſt is cauſeleſs? <hi>The hope of the righteous ſhall be gladneſs,</hi> Prov. 10.26. And <hi>we rejoyce in hope,</hi> Rom. 12.12.</p>
               <p>The deſign of <hi>Hope</hi> is conſider'd four ways. Firſt, it intends unto that which is <hi>good,</hi> which makes a difference between <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Fear:</hi> for we <hi>hope</hi> for that which is <hi>good,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:135920:19"/>
we <hi>fear</hi> that which is <hi>evil.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It is not that good which is <hi>preſent,</hi> but <hi>abſent;</hi> and this makes a difference between <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Fruition. Rom.</hi> 8.24. <hi>Hope that is ſeen, is not hope: for what a man ſeeth, why doth he yet hope for?</hi> Thirdly, Though it be a good ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and not yet obtained, yet it is <hi>poſſible;</hi> which is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Deſpair:</hi> but we have no colour for deſpair, ſince all things are poſſible to God. Fourthly, It is a poſſible good, but <hi>bonum arduum,</hi> to be gotten with difficulty and pains: which puts a difference between the diligence of Hope, and careleſs Security. Theſe are the four promontories of <hi>Hope,</hi> and a good wind blows from every quarter.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Firſt, It is good for a man to Hope, ſince we hope for that which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135920:19"/>
is <hi>good,</hi> ſo good, that it exceeds all that <hi>Eye</hi> hath ſeen: for as yet we ſee not God, but in his creatures. Nor <hi>Ear</hi> hath heard it, that is, in its full, unutterable excellency, which the words of Holy Scripture cannot expreſs to our imperfect rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Then <hi>neither can it enter into the heart of man:</hi> for things can ſeem no greater than words can ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>We know as yet but in part, hereafter we ſhall know as we are known.</hi> If we have boaſted to the Heathen that we look for a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and a Crown of glory, we are ſure we ſhall not be <hi>aſhamed</hi> of that hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. We may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that we have doted upon pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things, out of which we have deviſed felicity, and they have failed, and deceiv'd us: but our treaſure laid up in the Heaven is ſo ſure, that in the end, and in the day of trial none ſhall inſult over
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135920:20"/>
our hope, and ſay where is now the Lord your God? If a mortal man detain the wages of the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, 'tis a ſin: Therefore it cannot be incident to God, <hi>who is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous to forget our work, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of love,</hi> Heb. 6.10. <hi>We ſhall not always be forgotten: our Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation ſhall not periſh for ever,</hi> Pſal. 9.18. The judgment of a good eye-ſight is to ſee afar off; ſo is the judgment of a good hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark the unſpeakable reward of a better age to come. Whereupon it hath ſufficient ſatisfaction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leave, or to loſe all it hath, things <hi>not worthy to be compared to the glory which is revealed in us,</hi> Rom. 8.18. The rich Mines and Golden trade of both the <hi>Indies</hi> are on the other ſide the Line: ſo the rich trade of <hi>Hope</hi> is in the other world. Change your poor fraught, which is your lading in this veſſel
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135920:20"/>
of clay, and barter it for an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hope</hi> that is not under the embers, but mounts up in a trembling flame, reckons not what it is worth by a very little which it hath in hand, but by its ſhare which is reſerved in the ſtore-houſe of God's eternal recompence. Now I am abaſed, but there is mine honour, a far abundant exceeding weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Now I carry about a crazy ſickly body, there it ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and incident to no diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Now my neighbours and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance deſpiſe me, and run far from me; there I ſhall be enrolled with Angels and Saints, and with the Church of the firſt born, and with the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. Now I live in all diſorder of Church-ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in diſtraction of Schiſms, in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135920:21"/>
filthy ſtanch of old and new here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: but there is the new <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> where all things ſet forth the glory of the Lamb in beauty, and holineſs, and truth. Now I muſt die, and deliver up my body unto the duſt; but Chriſt died and roſe the third day, and will bring again with him in due time all thoſe that ſleep: and <hi>comfort one another with theſe words,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.14. And as when Chriſt aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Heaven, <hi>He went up with a merry noiſe, and the Lord with the ſound of the trumpet, Pſal.</hi> 47.5. So let every heart break out into praiſe and gladneſs, whoſe hope flies up unto the Lord in his holy places: <hi>Holding faſt the confidence, and the rejoycing of hope firm unto the end, Heb.</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Stay yet, and conſider it is a good which is <hi>abſent</hi> that we hope
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135920:21"/>
for: When it is come and brought to paſs, <hi>Hope</hi> is at the journeys end. <hi>Say to the righteous, it ſhall be well with him, for they ſhall eat the fruit of their doings,</hi> Iſa. 3.10. It ſhall be well, <hi>Dixit erit.</hi> It is not paid down, as we ſay, in ready money, but we have a good bond for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p>Let me object upon this, Doth not Hope deferr'd afflict the Soul? Yet be not diſheartened: it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ſo. For firſt we have ſomewhat in hand; becauſe that which <hi>Faith</hi> lays hold of, is really and actually its own: now <hi>Hope</hi> is <hi>Faith's</hi> rent-gatherer, and takes up that which <hi>Faith</hi> claims upon the bargain which Chriſt hath made for us.</p>
               <p>To be clearer yet: <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. <hi>verſes</hi> 13, 14. <hi>We are ſealed with the holy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135920:22"/>
Spirit of promiſe, which is the earneſt of our inheritance.</hi> You ſee then, that though we have not the <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance</hi> as yet, we have the <hi>earneſt</hi> of it; and an earneſt-penny is more than nothing. Here I muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between a <hi>pledge</hi> and an <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt.</hi> A <hi>pledge</hi> is laid down for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance to repay that which was lent: but an <hi>earneſt</hi> is given upon a bargain, to keep that till the reſt be brought in. Now the <hi>earneſt</hi> that we receive of the Kingdom to come, is the <hi>ſeal of the Spirit,</hi> an imprinted comfort that it ſhall be ours: A ſeal that cannot be defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, a comfort that cannot be taken from us. So much as you have of that <hi>ſeal,</hi> ſo much you have of the <hi>earneſt:</hi> therefore you cannot ſay that <hi>Hope</hi> hath quite nothing to ſtay its longing. The bloſſoms of the Spring do not only promiſe, but are God's earneſt, to repreſent the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135920:22"/>
fruits which will wax ripe in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn.</p>
               <p>I will make it out in another ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude. He that is in a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ware-houſe, where ſpices are ſtored up, ſhall have ſome taſte of them in his palate by their ſtrong ſcent, though he put not one corn into his mouth: ſo we taſte Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe the Spirit that comes from Heaven dwells in us, and gives many delightful ſigns of a glorified reverſion.</p>
               <p>But to go forward; it may not be denied but that <hi>Hope</hi> is anxious, and reſtleſs till it come to enjoy. How tedious a thing it is to ſtay long without the company of them, whom we entirely love? And can it be otherwiſe than irkſom, to be ſo long abſent from the viſion of God, and of Chriſt compaſſed with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135920:23"/>
innumerable Angels? St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays no leſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. <hi>We, that have the firſt fruits of the Spirit, groan within our ſelves, waiting for the adoption, to wit, the redemption of the body.</hi> Here are groans and ſighs indeed; but we ſhall never be Sea-ſick with that eaſie toſſing, having <hi>Hope as an anchor of our Soul, Heb.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Hope</hi> of the right ſtamp looking for the appearance of God, and the reward that he brings with him, hath a good Mate that goes together with it, and that's <hi>Patience.</hi> In the ſaddeſt book of the Scripture, <hi>Lamen.</hi> 3.26. it is written, <hi>It is good that a man ſhould hope, and quietly wait for the ſalvation of the Lord.</hi> Which that it may not be wanting, we muſt contend for it in prayer, as it is 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.5. <hi>The Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and the patient waiting for Chriſt.</hi> And it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135920:23"/>
is no difficult thing to be perſwaded. For when we are held off for a while from the inheritance of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, do we not attend God's lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? and will the handmaid wait for her Miſtreſs, being in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of place above her; and ſhall not the Creature ſtay the leiſure of the Creator ſo infinite above us? Beſide, the patient expectation of the recompence will increaſe the recompence, and make it more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative: therefore <hi>let not him that believes, make haſte, Iſa.</hi> 28.16. Nay, ſo your Spirit will be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, the Lord will allow you your importunity to call upon him to haſten; <hi>My strength, haſte thee to help me, Pſal.</hi> 22.19. Finally, ſtay for that contentedly, which when it comes, it comes but once, and ſhall abide for ever.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135920:24"/>III. Another degree upon which <hi>Hope</hi> ſteps higher is this, that her aim is <hi>poſſible.</hi> I have ſaid how that which is propoſed to it is <hi>good:</hi> that it is not diſconſolate, though it be in futurition, and not yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; (for it is too good to be yet obtained) if patience have its perfect work, it can attend chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. <hi>My ſoul wait thou only upon God, for my expectation is from him, Pſal.</hi> 62.5. Strike we therefore pleaſantly upon this third ſtring, that the paſt object of divine Hope is to be accompliſht. <hi>For I run not as uncertainly, I fight not as one that beateth the air,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Paul</hi> did do all things, and ſuffer all things, for that which is ſeizable, and might be atchieved.</p>
               <p>The covetous is a projector for ſo much wealth, as can never be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135920:24"/>
gotten. The Epicure longs for ſo much pleaſure, as can never be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd. Great Clerks and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſeek for ſo much knowledge, as can never be found: which in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> words, is <hi>to ſpend mony for that which is not bread, and to labour for that which doth not ſatisfie,</hi> Chap. 55.2. This is able to break the brain, and to break the heart: for there is no labour to loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>But the fruit of the righteous is a tree of life, Prov.</hi> 11.30. His <hi>Hope</hi> ſtands upon a ſound bottom: it is all comfort for three Reaſons. Firſt it is poſſible, becauſe it comes from an Infinite power. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is derived from Infinite love and goodneſs. 3. It hath abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſatisfaction from long and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant experience: and what can we deſire more?</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:135920:25"/>1. The firſt pillar that props it up is the Almightineſs of God. <hi>Abba Father, all things are poſſible to thee,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.16. Talk not to me how the Seas ſhould be turned into dry Land, or how the poor can be raiſed up to be ſet with the Princes of the people: or how ſtones can be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up to be children of <hi>Abraham:</hi> or how palſies and fevers can be cured with a word. I will ſtop all gaps of infidelity with this one buſh, <hi>That God is able to do it.</hi> He that is made by no Cauſe, cannot be confined in his Being: and he that hath no bounds in his Being, can have no bounds and reſtriction in his Power. And if any fancy ſtart out of our weak brain, to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil that ſomewhat is impoſſible to God, it is ſoberly ſpoken by one, that it were better to ſay that this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135920:25"/>
could not be done, than that God could not do it. There is no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility therefore for Chriſtian <hi>Hope</hi> to deſpair, becauſe all things are poſſible to God. There is no Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon under Heaven, or above Heaven, that <hi>Hope</hi> cannot look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it. For that comfort, that is commenſurable with the ſtrength and power of God, is as large as can be contained in the heart of a creature.</p>
               <p>But if you lean upon the help of men, and hoſts, and Angels, they are ſlender reeds, and will give you a fall: as God ſaid of the vain truſt of the <hi>Jews, They ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of</hi> Ethiopia <hi>their expectation, Iſa.</hi> 20.5. How many do I ſee to ſink under a little ſorrow, becauſe they have too much temporal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? the world is too liberal to them: it hath given them of all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135920:26"/>
things ſo largely, that they have not the patience to want any thing. As God told <hi>Gideon,</hi> that he had too much of Man in his Army to depend upon the Almighty for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and he bad him retain but the thirtieth part, and his foes ſhould flye before him, <hi>Jud.</hi> 7.4. Throw all the miſerable comforts of the world out of doors for rubbiſh, and caſt your ſelf upon the ſtrength of God, and upon that alone, and then ſay, Lord receive me, for I have driven all other ſolace from me, that I might enjoy thee alone: now I am ready for my Saviour, for there is none to help me, but only thou O Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, That which holy <hi>Hope</hi> hath in its proſpect is poſſible, not only for the Infiniteneſs of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, but for the Infiniteneſs of the mercy of our God. 'Tis eaſie to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135920:26"/>
get the favour of a gracious and a gentle nature among the ſons and daughters of men: and the moſt generous are the moſt reconcilable. Then what poſſibility, nay what readineſs will <hi>Hope</hi> find to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, <hi>merciful, gracious, long-ſuffering, abundant in goodneſs and truth? Exod.</hi> 34.6. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is not more frequent, nor more ſtrong in any temptation, than to undermine <hi>Hope</hi> in this point, that it is too forward, and too peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to expect remiſſion of ſins: fain he would have a tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſtick in this mire, and never get out of it. Some Reverend writers go ſo far to teach, that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan himſelf at firſt, when he began his miſchief in Paradiſe, was of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that ſin could not be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it being his own caſe: and that he would never have tempted <hi>Eve</hi> to diſobedience, if he had ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135920:27"/>
the eating of the forbidden fruit could be pardoned; not ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that God would have given his only Son to die for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which I paſs by, becauſe it depends upon a grave queſtion, whether God could pardon ſin by his abſolute power, without ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction made to his Juſtice? Deep diſputings will yield but ſhallow comforts: Of this we are aſſured, that the means which the Father appointed are excellent (into which, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>the Angels deſire to look</hi>) to give us <hi>redemption and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of ſins through the bloud of Chriſt, according to the riches of his grace,</hi> Eph. 1.7. <hi>We have treſpaſſed againſt our God, but there is hope concerning this thing,</hi> Ezra 10.2. <hi>Forgiveneſs of ſins</hi> is put into our Creed: he that doth not believe it, hath no Creed nor Chriſtianity in him. Do you believe <hi>a Catholick
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135920:27"/>
Church?</hi> that's the dowry of that Church, which Chriſt eſpouſed to him in his bloud. Do you believe <hi>a Communion of Saints?</hi> this is it in which we are baptized, in which all our communion doth joyn, <hi>That through Chriſt is preached for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of ſins, and by him all that believe are juſtified from all things, from which we could not be juſtified by the law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. <hi>verſes</hi> 38, 39. So alſo it is put into our prayer, as well as into our Creed. And he that taught us to pray, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our ſins,</hi> hath taught us this comfort, that ſins are pardonable.</p>
               <p>Yet an afflicted Conſcience will receive ſuggeſtion, that ſome ſins indeed are pardonable, but not all, not the ſin of the evil Angels, not the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt: and <hi>there is a ſin unto death, I do not ſay ye ſhould pray for it,</hi> ſays St. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:135920:28"/>
1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 5.16. Theſe verily are ſet out for inſtances of irreverſible judgment, to deter us from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting crimes of a vaſt magnitude. But mark, the Holy Scriptures have not unfolded it clearly and explicitly, wherein the hainouſneſs of theſe ſins did conſiſt, that we may not accuſe our ſelves of them, and fall into deſpair, as if we had committed them. Since you know not expreſly what theſe are, how can you lay them to your own charge? Nay, if you lay them to your own charge, you muſt be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken: for he that condemns him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſhall not be condemned of the Lord. Such incurable caſt-aways have their Conſciences ſeared, and are not ſenſible of their guilt. Who more like to be of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber than the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves, ſaying, Are we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo blind?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:135920:28"/>Well, ſays a forlorn ſinner, my ſins then are not the fore-named, nor out of poſſibility of mercy; but it is almoſt as bad, that they are in an unlikelihood to mercy; for they are very hainous. As unto that confeſſion that your treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes are very hainous, conceive ſo of them, and ſpare not: true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance thinks no ſin to be a little one. So St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſpake to the commendation of the Lady <hi>Paula</hi> in her Funeral Sermon, that ſhe was wont to bewail every fault ſhe had committed, as if it were one of the moſt preſumptuous crimes. But be it ſo really, that God hath let you incur no ſmall delinquencies: as <hi>Aaron</hi> was not free from idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, nor <hi>David</hi> from adultery, nor <hi>Peter</hi> from abjuration of Chriſt, nor <hi>Paul</hi> from perſecuting the Church, nor <hi>Manaſſes</hi> from witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135920:29"/>
nor <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite ſcandal, well, I know not what; who yet all obtained mercy, for a pattern to them who hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould believe in Chriſt to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. They were called <hi>Novatians,</hi> who blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out the beginning of the Eighth Chapter of St. <hi>John's</hi> Goſpel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſtory tells us, that Chriſt diſmiſt the woman taken in adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with a gracious gentleneſs. Why ſhould not his procedure in judgment be like his doctrine? did he not preach that Publicans and Harlots ſhould go into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before proud Juſticiaries? <hi>Be merciful unto my ſin, for it is great,</hi> ſays <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 25.11. This is not the way to deal with mortal Judges, when we ſtand at their bar; but this is the way to obtain propitiation from our God; Heal me, for I am ſore wounded; cure
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135920:29"/>
me, for I am very ſick; be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to my ſin, for it is very great. <hi>Zozimus</hi> a Pagan that envied the honour of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, makes this tale to diſcredit him in his Hiſtory; that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had put his wife <hi>Fauſta,</hi> and his ſon <hi>Criſpus</hi> to death: after which being haunted with an ill Conſcience that gave him no quiet, he ſought among the Heathen Prieſts for expiation, and they could give him no peace: but he was told that the Religion of Chriſtians was ſo audacious, as to promiſe pardon to all ſins, were they never ſo horrible. Is not this to commend the Emperor and his Religion under the form of a diſpraiſe? for what reſt could a troubled mind attain to, from the Rites and Superſtitions of Idol-gods? But in the immenſe value of the price of the bloud of Chriſt there is redemption for every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135920:30"/>
that repents and believes. <hi>Whatſoever ye looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven,</hi> ſays Chriſt to his Apoſtles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18. O loſe not a ſyllable of ſuch comfort in this diſcomfortable world. <hi>Quodcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> is all manner of ſin, great and little. And if Chriſt hath given ſuch commiſſion to men on Earth, to unlooſe every ſin by the power of their office, and the word of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, then how unbounded is his own clemency? No ſins can ſuper-abound his grace, if we do not ſin preſumptuouſly, becauſe grace abounds.</p>
               <p>Yet the poor <hi>Publican</hi> will beat his breaſt, and cry out dolefully, My ſins are many, they are more in number than the hairs of my head. The bill of endictment is a true bill: who can tell how oft he offendeth? Scarce any ſin we act
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135920:30"/>
but hath a neſt of ſins in it: then think we what a heap will they make, when they are put all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Peter,</hi> it ſeems, miſdoubted, that if a man were forgiven, that had treſpaſt often, it would be ſcandalous, and encourage the offender, therefore he thought it fit to ſtint indulgence to ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity, as it is, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Lord, how oft ſhall my brother ſin againſt me, and I forgive him? un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſeven times? Jeſus anſwereth, I ſay not unto thee, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil ſeven times, but, until ſeventy times ſeven times:</hi> ſo that Chriſt commends a bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs forgiveneſs in a finite number for an infinite. And doubtleſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would not ſtick with us for the ſame number. God forbid we ſhould think he taught to be more merciful, or of greater perfection than himſelf. <hi>Her ſins which are many, are forgiven,</hi> Luke 7.47.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:135920:31"/>Be thankful and admire the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of our Father, both for nailing our great ſins to the Croſs of Chriſt, and for acquitting us from the innumerable fry of Minim-ſins, thoſe of daily incurſion; becauſe when one of the leaſt is remitted, all are remitted together. Mark that conſiderately. One that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome ſoul and leprous ſin, goes mourning upon the deep ſenſe of it, and eſpecially the horror of it makes him fear damnation: yet he greatly deceives himſelf, if he think his other ſins are paſt over, and this great one, or a few ſuch do remain to his perdition. For do you hope comfortably that ſome faults of omiſſion, ſome idle words, ſome gariſh and cuſtomary faſhion of pride are remitted to you? with the ſame affiance, leaning on Chriſt, you may hope that you are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135920:31"/>
from your greateſt enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. For all unrighteouſneſs is covered at once to them with whom God is well pleaſed. No ſin is forgiven to him that is not in Chriſt, and againſt him that is in Chriſt there is no condemnation. They are the ſons of God, to whom the Lord doth graciouſly remit any fault: but where any fault is not remitted, they are his enemies. He that is juſtified from any ſin, muſt be truly penitent: but a true penitent is ſorry for all ſins toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; hates them, eſchews them all alike. Then follows a plenary abſolution from all iniquity through Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>And beware that you over-look not theſe multitudes of ſins of the under ſize, as if little grief or anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety would ſerve for them: are they not numberleſs corns of ſand? and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135920:32"/>
may not a weight of too much ſand ſink a ſhip, as ſoon as a burden of too much iron? The dailineſs of ſin muſt be bewailed with the daili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſorrow. And then <hi>when thou lieſt down, thou ſhalt not be afraid, yea thou ſhalt lie down, and thy ſleep ſhall be ſweet, Prov.</hi> 3.24. Now tell me if this balm be not enough to heal the bleedings and bruiſings of deſpair? Talents of ſin, and ſins in ſmall mony, you may hide them all in the wounds of Chriſt. It is poſſible for God to do the benefit, and poſſible for thee to receive it. <hi>Let Iſrael hope in the Lord: for with the Lord there is mercy, and with him is plenteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; and he ſhall redeem</hi> Iſrael <hi>from all his iniquities,</hi> Pſalm 130. verſe <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It muſt now be added, how that which <hi>Hope</hi> waits for is poſſible,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135920:32"/>
ſince it may find ſatisfaction from long and conſtant experience. In the yonger days of the world ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what might be ſaid to excuſe the backwardneſs of Hope: they want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed proof and demonſtration in thoſe times. Even <hi>Cain</hi> was the ſooner overtaken with deſpair, crying out, <hi>My ſin is greater than can be forgiven me:</hi> He had not lived ſo long to be taught the contrary by experience. But every age hath given advantage to <hi>Hope</hi> to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied better and better. <hi>O God, we have heard with our ears, and our fathers have declared unto us the noble works that thou didſt in their days, and in the old time before them, Pſalm</hi> 44.1. The records of God do tell us how the Armies of aliens have been diſcomfited before his Children, how the rocks have given them drink, and the barren wilderneſs bread; how the Church
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135920:33"/>
hath been ſcattered and recollect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the righteous continually ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported either with deliverance or patience: that the dead have been raiſed up to life: nay, that <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> were taken up alive into Heaven, to implant into our minds, that both they that are in the graves ſhall hear the voice of Chriſt, and come forth; and that ſuch as ſhall be found living at that day ſhall be caught up in the clouds, and be tranſlated into Heaven. And I challenge <hi>Hope</hi> to inſtance, if it can ſurmiſe that any thing is impoſſible to be brought to paſs, ſince there is a preſident in every thing to demonſtrate, that the right hand of the Lord hath brought mighty things to paſs. There is one thing, I confeſs, for which there is no example, neither can be evidenced, till all things be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht, that is the coming of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135920:33"/>
Lord Chriſt with the new Heavens and the new Earth: and yet, to confirm us in that myſtery to come, St. <hi>John</hi> did ſee the Idea or glimpſe of it in his Revelation.</p>
               <p>The uſe of all this is to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the tranſactions of God in the times that are gone before. Who ever ſaw the righteous forſaken? or the wicked flouriſh long? was there ever any perſecution of the Church, which hath not ended in its triumph? But ſtay for it, and pray for it, and condole for the delays of God's providence, till you may ſay in earneſt, <hi>My ſoul fainteth for thy ſalvation, Pſalm</hi> 119.31. How eaſie is it for a Chriſtian, that hath any noſtril, to run after God in the odour of his ſweet ointments, and trace his ſteps from point to point? and then to ſay with <hi>David, I have remembred
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135920:34"/>
thy judgments of old,</hi> O Lord, and have comforted my ſelf, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.52. and from another Prophet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Ye ſhall ſee their way, and their doings, and ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted concerning all the evil that I have brought upon</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
               <p>The great ſtore-houſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation is <hi>Hope;</hi> therefore all this, and more muſt be ſaid to keep it freſh, like a green Olive-tree, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never a ſear or withered bough upon it. I come now to complete it; I have ſhewn it aims only at <hi>good,</hi> and that which is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and excellently good: at ſuch a good whoſe harveſt is not brought in all in a year, but ſtill there is more and more to be had, and the moſt to come: It is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible through the greatneſs of Gods power and mercy, as all ages have witneſſed.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:135920:34"/>IV. But laſtly, that which may ſeem to pinch is, that it is <hi>Bonum arduum,</hi> a good not eaſily attained, but with great labour and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to give warning againſt ſloth and ſecurity. It were not worth our longing to ſay we hope for petty things, eaſie, and at hand; but for things of value, for which we muſt ſtruggle with many lets and impediments to poſſeſs them. No man need to hope to find Cockle-ſhells on the ſhore: but to find Pearls in the Sea, that's an object for the adventure of a Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eller. Neither is the Jewel of Chriſtian <hi>Hope</hi> eaſily purchaſt. But as <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eliſha, Thou haſt asked a hard thing: nevertheleſs if thou ſee me, when I am taken from thee, it ſhall be ſo unto thee,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.10. Much after that ſort I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with my heart, and ſay, It
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135920:35"/>
is good to ſeek for eternal life, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it as the Hart brayeth after the rivers of waters: there will be much a-do to get it, for <hi>many ſhall ſeek to enter in, and ſhall not be able, Luke</hi> 13.24. Nevertheleſs, if thou canſt ſee the Lord, as if he were continually before thee, thou ſhalt not miſs of that thou deſireſt: for all things are poſſible to him, whoſe eyes are ever toward the Lord.</p>
               <p>Theſe difficulties upon which I ſtrike, are either <hi>in our ſelves,</hi> or <hi>in our adventure:</hi> in our ſelves partly through natural imbecillity, partly through contracted impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our natural languor is that of original contagion, which makes us ſo weak, that there is none that doth good, no not one. Which is not to be extenuated, as if the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135920:35"/>
of it might be ſuppreſt with a little reſiſtance. It is good to know the power of ſo ſtrong an enemy, that we may be fortified againſt it. It is a root of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs never to be digg'd up out of corrupt nature: a coal of fire ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out ſparks of temptations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually: as inward to us as the marrow is in our bones. Yet there is hope in Chriſt to ſlake this fire, though not utterly in this life to quench it. It is a body of death, a whole body, conſiſting of all the members of ſin; yet a body is but fleſh, and a Spirit is mightier than fleſh. Apply that of the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> to it, as we may read it by the direction of our Margent, and keep to the Original, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. <hi>If it be difficult in the eyes of this people, ſhall it be difficult in mine eyes, ſaith the Lord?</hi> Therefore ſince God is our help againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135920:36"/>
of this rebellious ſin, let us be comforted in his help, and not in excuſes. For we muſt not plead our perſonal maladies, and natural inclinations, and think that God will take it for an anſwer, and ask no more.</p>
               <p>I am dull of underſtanding, ſays one, and what I am taught I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear it away. I am ſuddenly tranſported with indignation, and cannot chuſe but break out: I am retentive of an injury, and cannot eaſily be reconciled. All this, and the like is no better than the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of thoſe ill manner'd gueſts in the Goſpel, which were invited to a Feaſt made by a King, <hi>We cannot come, I pray you have us excuſed:</hi> which ſounds like confeſſion and humility, but it is denial and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Spend your breath in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way, and cry out often and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135920:36"/>
Give me not over to my ſelf O Lord, take away from me my ſtony heart, and give me an heart of fleſh. Drop down upon this barren earth, and it ſhall bring forth quite againſt the byaſs of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The high minded will grow meek as a Lamb, the covetous will begin to diſperſe and ſcatter abroad, the lying lips will confeſs the truth, bitter cruelty will melt into pity, new-fangled braveries will be laid aſide and bluſh at vanity. To what purpoſe are the pourings in of the Spirit, but that what is wickedly in-bred from our concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould be ſhaken off from the tree, and a better fruit ſpring up in the place from the increaſe of God?</p>
               <p>Mark the rain that falls from above, and the ſame ſhower, that dropt out of one cloud, increaſeth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135920:37"/>
ſundry plants in a garden, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally according to the condition of every plant: in one ſtalk it makes a Roſe, in another a Violet, divers in a third, and ſweet in all. So the Spirit works its multifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous effects in ſeveral complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of God. Is thy habit and inclination cholerick? why, try thy ſelf, if thou be very apt to be zealous in a good cauſe, and it turns thy natural infirmity into ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heat. Is melancholy predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? the grace of God will turn that ſad humor into devotion, prayer, and mortifying thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to die unto the world. Is thy temperature ſanguine and chearful? the goodneſs of God will allow it unto thee in thy civil life in a good mean; but over and above it will make thee bountiful, eaſie to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don injuries, glad of reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135920:37"/>
comfortable to the diſtreſſed, always rejoycing in the Lord. Is a man phlegmatick and fearful? if this freezing diſeaſe, which is in thee from thy mothers womb, be not abſolutely cured, yet the Holy Ghoſt will work upon it, to make thy Conſcience tender, wary to give no offence, to make thee pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, penitent, contrite, ready to weep for thy tranſgreſſions. There are two handles to take hold of every thing, ſays a Heathen: A diſſolute man takes hold of original frailties, and makes them Serpents: a holy man declines their Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine nature, and catcheth them by that part, which may conduce to all manner of vertue. This is the comfort of <hi>Hope</hi> againſt original inquination, that this great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, by the operation of the Spirit, ſhall be made our friend, or our foot-ſtool. <hi>O wretched man that I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135920:38"/>
am! who ſhall deliver me from this body of death? I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Rom. 7.24.</p>
               <p>What is ſtronger than a Lion? yet, if the Lion be kill'd, <hi>out of the strong comes forth ſweetneſs, Jud.</hi> 14.14. For all this the worſt is not paſt: beſide natural pronity to ſin, we have contracted much more evil by cuſtom, education, ſtrong habits, noxious examples, bad en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements and infuſions. The Cockatrice-egge was laid, when we were in our mothers womb, but it proves more venemous being hatcht, and grown able to flye abroad. There are ſeventy ſons of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who ſhall kill thee? Even the ſword of the Spirit: <hi>There is none like it,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of that of <hi>Goliah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.9. This is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, not merely to cut down graſs and briars, but to hew down the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135920:38"/>
tree, to cut off the branches, to ſhake the leaves, to ſcatter the fruit, to fright away the fowls from the branches, and the beaſts from grazing under it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 14. or as the Apoſtle comforts us in plain words, without a Parable, <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt that strengtheneth me,</hi> Phil. 4.13.</p>
               <p>If you be over-toiled and heated too much, you know how to cool: caſt off ſome garments, wipe away the ſweat, ſit ſtill and ſtir not, leſt you enflame your ſelf with motion. Follow the ſame method, lay aſide the burden of ſin, that enflames you, caſt off the weight and the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of naughtineſs: bear in mind that Chriſt ſweat drops of bloud in his Agony, to make you aſhamed of toiling and ſweating in Satan's drudgery. Take eaſe in a Sabbath of holy reſt, and moil not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135920:39"/>
in the unprofitable works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Try what refrigeration this will give unto your Conſcience: elſe take heed that you be not put to a terrible ſweat of fear, leſt God take you away in his wrath, and give you up for ever to Satan, whom you have ſerved ſo willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony:</hi> mind no examples, but when they are wrapt up therein. <hi>Be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to this world, but be ye tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the renewing of your mind, Rom.</hi> 12.2. What a caſe had <hi>Noah</hi> been in, if he had framed his life by common practice, when all fleſh had corrupted their way? Chuſe better company, as <hi>Enoch</hi> did to walk with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. And <hi>can two walk together, unleſs they be agreed? Amos</hi> 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 3. It is more than agreement: it imports endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135920:39"/>
benevolence, friendſhip with God. No title can be greater, or ſweeter: what can match that honour of <hi>Abraham</hi> and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to be called the <hi>friends</hi> of God, and Chriſt? No league in the world more ſought for, or more willingly accepted: no amity leſs burdenſom, or more beneficial. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> 8. <hi>Confeſſ. Cap.</hi> 6. brings in a couple that ſerved the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor thus debating upon it. What can we look for in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, more than to be call'd the <hi>friends</hi> of our Soveraign? When we have got this, it is no ſure and unchangeable favour. And how long ſhall we attend before we be promoted to it? But let us turn to God in this hour, and ſue to be his <hi>friends,</hi> and it ſhall be done in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and remain eternally. <hi>Ask and it ſhall be given, ſeek and we ſhall find.</hi> And as we treſpaſs by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135920:40"/>
ſins of daily prevention, there is a dailineſs of mercy to comfort us. But as you love Chriſt, and would be beloved, ſtruggle with tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, do not yield upon the firſt enticement, no nor upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or third aſſault. <hi>Reſiſt the Devil, and he will fly from you:</hi> quit your ſelf like a man, fight like a Chriſtian: <hi>The fleſh is weak, but the Spirit is willing, ready, able to aſſiſt you, Matth.</hi> 26.41. Thus Hope waxeth valiant, and aſſures it ſelf of victory againſt cuſtoms, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and all contracted impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Lay now our adventure, the toil and peril of our labour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are employ'd, in another ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and more difficulty will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. For <hi>Hope</hi> is wiſe, and doth not flatter it ſelf, as if the Kingdom of Heaven were acceſſible with
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135920:40"/>
little pains. What carefulneſs ought this to work in us? what ſelf-denial? what fear? what zeal? what unblamable converſation? <hi>I run, I fight, I keep under my body, and bring it into ſubjection,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.27. <hi>For Chriſt Jeſus I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the loſs of all things, Phil.</hi> 3.8. Chriſt, having overcome the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of death, hath opened the kingdom of Heaven to all belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: yet to put us to our skill and labour to follow, mark what he hath taught us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Strait is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore is it ſo <hi>strait and narrow?</hi> a queſtion worthy to be reſolved, to teach us, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us.</p>
               <p>Firſt, a very religious life is ſaid
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135920:41"/>
by a Metaphor to go in at a ſtrait gate, becauſe it is our maſter-piece to find the door, or to begin well; therefore it is call'd <hi>to be born again.</hi> For as to be born into the world needs more art, and skilful Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifery, than to bring us up: ſo to be regenerate, to begin to live the life that is in Chriſt, is exceeding irkſom to fleſh and bloud: ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the enticements that throng about the way, to keep us from the door, and to hold us in love with thoſe ſins, which have been our companions. As an Orator will be more timorous to deliver the firſt period of his ſpeech, than all that follows; ſo we ſtick long at the firſt on-ſet to reform, to be ſtrict, to paſs away with ſo much vanity as muſt be forſaken. The penitent thief could not find the door till he was going out of the world: St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as ſome compute,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135920:41"/>
was twenty eight years old before he left to be a blaſphemer. But ruſh on, and make way through all reſiſtances: he that hath one foot over the threſhold, and hath caſt the world behind him, is well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced into the courts of our God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, A Heavenly mind ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it ſelf up into one wiſh, and no more. <hi>One thing have I deſired of the Lord, which I will require, Pſal.</hi> 27.4. Grant me thy ſelf, O Lord, and I will ask no more. The new creature asks nothing of God, but to enjoy God: give me this, O Lord, and for the reſt let <hi>Ziba</hi> take all. I will part with all to buy that one Pearl, the riches of Heavenly grace. The ſervant of ſin hath all manner of pleaſures under Heaven to trade in. Can he ask for a ſhop with more variety of ware? why may he not have theſe,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135920:42"/>
you will ſay, and life eternal to boot? Some of them are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with life eternal; but all are not, ſo they be added, and not ſought for; as our Saviour diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth, <hi>Firſt ſeek the kingdom of God, and theſe things ſhall be added, Matth.</hi> 6.33. But if you ſeek them, (which is to love them for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) and above the kingdom of God, it is like a man that carries a piece of timber at bredth upon his back; there is no door wide enough for a man to get in with ſuch an impediment upon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. It is not the gate that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes him, but he thruſts himſelf out with his own improvidence.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, There are thouſands of ſcandals, millions of errors to be avoided, but truth and holineſs are in the middle, in a little compaſs; and happy is he that ſhuns ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135920:42"/>
and falls perpendicularly upon the golden mean. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God are but <hi>ten words, Deut.</hi> 4.13. the inventions of men, and the forms of will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are innumerous. <hi>Pray, Faſt, give Alms,</hi> Chriſt comprehends much external duty under thoſe three Heads, but the Traditions of men are more than can be put into a Catalogue. <hi>Call upon God in the time of trouble,</hi> that and no more is the Pole-ſtar of Faith in Prayer; but what a compaſs doth <hi>Monkiſhneſs</hi> take in, to drop beads in the invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Angels and Saints? Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs neglects the honour of God: Superſtition falls into need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs exceſſes about it: the true fear of God is in the centre, as far from the one extream as from the other. As in an accurate Song you muſt keep Minim-time, or elſe you will put the whole Quire out; ſo look
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135920:43"/>
that you ſing the new ſong of the Lord with trembling and accurate obſervation, miſs neither Cliff nor Note, that is, neither ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, nor pious practice.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Reaſons why it is ſo hard to get acceſs to Chriſt in a narrow way, and through a ſtrait gate. If theſe difficulties be not diſcern'd by ſome, it is becauſe they take up Chriſtianity as it is in uſe among men, and as they are born to it. But they that came to it in their years of underſtanding, and were trained up in Church-diſcipline many years before they were baptized, and all that time were put to exact trial what they would prove, and were taught it over and over, how the Laws of Chriſt were far ſtricter than any other Laws in the world; theſe were preacquainted with the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135920:43"/>
which they muſt perform, and then received it, with the larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and hardeſt conditions. Yet they were brought on with two ſpecial comforts: Firſt, that God did behold from Heaven the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs of the task which we took upon us, the troubles of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the dangers of temptations, the infirmities of man to reſiſt them: <hi>He knows whereof we are made, he remembreth we are but duſt:</hi> it puts him to admire the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of his Saints, as <hi>Jeſus</hi> marvelled at the <hi>Centurion</hi>'s Faith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.10. Secondly, when we are under our hazards, we ſhall have an anſwer from the Lord, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> had, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee, for my strength is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in weakneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. Therefore as the Lord ſaid of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> when he had choſen him, <hi>I have laid help upon one that is mighty,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135920:44"/>
Pſalm</hi> 89.19. So we caſting our ſelves upon the help of God, upon one that is Almighty; though of our ſelves we have gathered little into our Omer, the bleſſing of God upon it will not let us lack. Every hard matter that roſe among the people was to be brought to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 18.16. ſo in every hard cauſe deſire the Lord to plead it, and to judge it; bring it to him, leave it in his Court, and he will end it. Theſe are the Cordials to revive <hi>Hope,</hi> touching the difficulties it finds, in the way to obtain that Good which is ſet before it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:135920:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> How a Chriſtian's Comforts flow from the Inhabitation and Teſtimony of the Holy Ghoſt; as alſo from the Sanctification of the Spirit unto all Obedience, and the fruits of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</head>
               <p>I Have inſiſted with ſo much length, and variety upon <hi>Hope,</hi> becauſe it is the largeſt in-let of Chriſtian Conſolation. Yet in the third place, that which carries it on, nay, that which cauſeth it, is <hi>the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> As the Air is the <hi>medium</hi> through which the Eye doth ſee all things, yet it is the light that ſhines in it that makes all things viſible: ſo <hi>Hope</hi> is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135920:45"/>
means, enlivened by <hi>Faith,</hi> through which we rejoyce with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory; yet it is <hi>the Spirit inhabiting</hi> that kindles it, that enlightens it, which makes it affect its object, and cleave unto it. Our Saviour left the world, and aſcended into Heaven for many reaſons, one was to give gifts unto men; which gifts, though very many, are all united in their Fountain, the Holy Ghoſt. Of which legacy Chriſt gave warning before his death, <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.16. <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever.</hi> Verſe 17. <hi>The world knows him not, becauſe it ſees him not: but ye know him, for he ſhall dwell with you, and ſhall be in you.</hi> Verſe 18. <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſs, I will come to you.</hi> Chap. 16. verſe 7. <hi>If I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135920:45"/>
but if I depart, I will ſend him unto you.</hi> This Comforter, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Spirit, to ſpeak after the phraſe of men, is the Proxy of Chriſt, his repreſentative in our hearts. And ſo it was fulfilled: for when the Spirit deſcended in great abundance upon the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. ſays St. <hi>Peter, This is that which is come to paſs.</hi> Verſe 28. <hi>Thou haſt made known to me the ways of life; thou ſhalt make me full of joy with thy countenance.</hi> And for the evidence of it, it is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.31. <hi>The Churches were edified, walking in the fear of God, and in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Which Text begets this note, That Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſolace conſiſts in two things, which we may call the <hi>Root</hi> and the <hi>Fruit.</hi> The Root is the Holy Ghoſt taking up his Tabernacle in us, ſo that <hi>our Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt which is in us,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:135920:46"/>
6.19. To walk by it in the fear of God is the Fruit of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all manner of obedience.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Unto the former, <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling of the Spirit,</hi> let this be premiſed. When we ſpeak of any one dwelling in ſafety, the great queſtion is, Who keeps the houſe? When <hi>David</hi> fled from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for fear of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> there was no likelihood that his Palace would hold out, for he left ten women, that were Concubines to keep the Houſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. <hi>verſe</hi> 16. So if we leave our Concubines, our luſts and carnal deſires to keep our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they will betray us to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to get the poſſeſſion. But who can take the City, if the Lord keep it, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 127.1. How impregnable are we, if he dwell in us, and we in him, <hi>becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit,</hi> 1 Jo. 4.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:135920:46"/>All that one can ſay unto this, who is doubtful in Faith, will be, Shew me that the Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and that the God of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is entred into me, and it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth. I anſwer, I cannot ſhew, that is, demonſtrate it to another, that this eternal life is in him; but I can perſwade an apt Scholler to ſtir up the Grace which is in him, that he may ſhew it to himſelf. I ſay he may do it, if he give his mind to it. Elſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> made a queſtion to no purpoſe, <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?</hi> 1 Cor. 3.16.</p>
               <p>I deny not but the Devil hath a way to fetch it about, to make you miſ-know, and take no heed of that you do perceive, if he did not ſtagger you with deluſions. This
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135920:47"/>
is the firſt leſſon that he reads out of his Morals, That diſtruſt is a high point of wiſdom; and be not over-reacht with opinion: you are ſure of that you ſee, and of no more. But to meet with this fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy: Is nothing certain, or at leaſt ſo certain as that which may be ſeen? Why, the Wind will blow away this objection, the Air will confute it. What can you make up ſo cloſe that the Air and the Wind will not get into it? Yet you ſee it not, you know not whence it comes, it is an inviſible meſſenger: <hi>So is every one that is born of the Spirit, Jo.</hi> 3.8. Breath is an imperceptible expiration, therefore Chriſt breathed on his Apoſtles, and ſaid, <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt, Jo.</hi> 20.22. Some gales of Weſtern winds in the Spring make the Earth glad with their gentle blaſt, and open the Buds
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135920:47"/>
and Flowers: ſo there is a breath of Omnipotent vertue which fans the heart that was hot in ſin with its coolneſs, which carries away the Caterpillars that eat up the tender leaf of our firſt greenneſs: which widens our bloſſoms to make their expectation ſhew it ſelf openly: which perfumes the evil ſcents of ſcandals that annoy us, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to that intent in the myſtical Song, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Awake thou North wind, and come thou South, and blow upon my Garden, that the ſpices thereof may flow out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I bring the caſe again to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd: Is no witneſs ſo compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to depoſe for truth, unleſs it be ſenſible, and chiefly diſcerned by the Eye? then what ail all Sects of Philoſophers to ſay, That the Sun, and all the Stars above work upon theſe Bodies below by heat and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135920:48"/>
light, and likewiſe by influence? An inviſible vertue that doth enter into the production of many effects; which ſeems to have God's appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation with his own voice, <hi>Job</hi> 38.31. who mentions there <hi>the ſweet influences of Pleiades,</hi> and <hi>the bands of Orion.</hi> And can the Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Firmament drop down good upon Minerals and Plants, upon Man and Beaſt, and by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret derivation? What an error, or rather what a madneſs is it then, to ſcruple whether he that made the Heavens can dart Celeſtial beams into man's Soul, without a ſenſible perception? And this is all I will ſay more unto it: Is not the Soul of Man above a material apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? <hi>Pliny,</hi> or <hi>Galen,</hi> or whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever unadviſedly deny the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of it, will yield there is a Soul in our compoſition, that holds all the parts of the Body together,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135920:48"/>
and moves, and acts in them: yet they can as ſoon take a Penſil, and paint an Eccho, as deſcribe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible nature of a Soul, by <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> drawn out in our ſenſitive fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Therefore it concerns us in maintenance of the dignity of our own nature to ſay, That the Spirit of God can inform our Soul, as well as our Soul can inform our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. I know not what temptation may riſe to gain-ſay the truth, That the Soul is known by her powers and operations, that it juſtifies it ſelf to be an Immaterial ſubſtance, a ſpark kindled in us by God, from Reaſon, and Will, and Memory. But what evidence is there that there is a Divine cauſe that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in, and is more than theſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Faculties?</p>
               <p>It is requiſite to work cloſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this queſtion: and I anſwer.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135920:49"/>
Firſt, becauſe the bounds of nature are known, beyond which nature cannot reach forth it ſelf: as it works in its own ſphere to preſerve it ſelf in being, and in well-being, in health, in wealth, in fame and glory, in extending our ſelves unto ages to come by leaving a poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in preſerving our Country where we are born, and the like. But to have our converſation in Heaven, at this preſent in Heaven, to aſcend thither in our deſires, and in the tendencies of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to aſpire to live in bleſſedneſs for ever, to long to be at that reſt, where there is no ſin; to look for a Church which hath neither ſpot nor wrinkle: this could not enter into us to proſecute it all induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, conſtantly, chearfully, but by a ſupernatural elevation, (far above the vigour of a Soul preſt down by a corruptible Body) that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135920:49"/>
is, by the power of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I feel the pulſe of that Divine Spirit beating in me by <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in tribulations</hi> for Chriſts ſake, and <hi>taking pleaſure in infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> upon the ſame ſcore, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. And again, <hi>I am filled with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, I am exceeding joyful in all our tribulations,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.4. An obſtinate Pagan might arm himſelf with patience and reſolution to vex his perſecutors, and rather fall into them, than decline them, out of ſpight and contumacy. But Self-love being ſpun out of our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, bred in the bone; who could rejoyce to endure anguiſh upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, that God might be glorified, but by ſtrength which we are not born unto, but which is given us, becauſe we are born again of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:135920:50"/>Go farther yet. How much is the content of a natural man laid aſide, when a good Chriſtian in his deliberate thoughts ſometimes prays to have the rebellions of his heart kept under by ſome expedient croſs? wiſheth, for wholſom cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to beat down the rankneſs of his ſins? expects God's fan to winnow the chaff from the wheat? For he knows, that as too much light dazles the Eyes, ſo too much proſperitie ſurfeits the mind. Therefore a good practitioner in Repentance perceives, there is no better way to bring him in from his wandrings, than to be ſcourged home with the gentle hand of God. To which ſome Expoſitors ſay the Spouſe alludes, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.5. (read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one word as it is right in our Margent) <hi>Turn away thine eyes from me, for they have puffed me up.</hi> If
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135920:50"/>
we be puffed up, it is time to pray that the eye of God's outward mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy be for a little turned from us. But where had nature learnt that Leſſon, if the Holy Ghoſt had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taught it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, As the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>No man hates his own fleſh.</hi> Every man, not overcome with a phrenzy of melancholy, loves his own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and would preſerve his life. The Devil, that cannot die, knows how loth we are to die: <hi>All that a man hath will he give for his life, Job</hi> 2.4. But how many Saints have undergone, how many more are willing to undergo the fiery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and offer up their bodies for the teſtimony of the Lord <hi>Jeſus?</hi> not to be cried up in popularity: not to be enrolled in the ſame of an Hiſtory, as there was ſuch a ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling among the Heathen. But they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135920:51"/>
have died like Lambs in the midſt of Wolves, when they have been hated, and evil ſpoken of in exceſs, becauſe they would die for the truth of the Goſpel, which their perſecutors accounted to be blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt the Gods which they worſhipped. If Parents, or Wives, or Children hung upon their arms, and beſought them with tears to ſpare themſelves, they threw them off as Chriſt did <hi>Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan, thou art an offence unto me, Matth.</hi> 16. <hi>verſe</hi> 22. To ſee a Martyr at the point of death feel no horror in his fleſhly nature, but to be raiſed up as high as the third Heavens with zeal; what humane power could bring him to it? nothing but the Holy Ghoſt did, as I may ſay, lure his Soul out of the Body, with a bait of a Crown of Glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:135920:51"/>Fourthly, <hi>The fruits of the Spirit are love, joy, peace, goodneſs, faith, temperance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. Is not the Tree known by the fruit? Such a cluſter hanging all together, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſtantly, and being fair and ſound <hi>(Tota, in toto tempore, cum toto corde)</hi> it is not poſſible that they ſhould grow like a Bull-ruſh out of the mud of corrupt nature. <hi>No man can ſay that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. that is, ſay it effectually, and from true allegiance to ſerve him as a Lord; for elſe Chriſt will ſay, <hi>Why call you me Lord, Lord, and do not the thing which I ſay, Luke</hi> 6.46. This is the Spirit that acts not only in propheſies and miraculous gifts, but in every child of God. Even in the old Teſtament, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.20. <hi>Thou gaveſt thy good Spirit to inſtruct them:</hi> them, that is, thoſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135920:52"/>
that were led out of <hi>Egypt</hi> by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and hearkened to him. And much more in the ſtate of the New Teſtament, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. <hi>The love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This might be extended into a great length, that the Holy Ghoſt is the <hi>Comforter,</hi> called ſo by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation, though it belong to every perſon of the Holy Trinity, and is well expreſt in the firſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Song, which is Printed before the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David</hi> in Meeter,
<q>
                     <l>Thou art the very Comſorter</l>
                     <l>in all woe and diſtreſs;</l>
                     <l>The Heavenly gift of God moſt high</l>
                     <l>which no tongue can expreſs.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This is <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, which we have from the Holy One,</hi> 1 Epiſt. Jo.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135920:52"/>
2.20. <hi>The anointing which we have received of him that abideth in you,</hi> Verſe 27. Anointing-oil is an oil to cure the ſick, <hi>James</hi> 5. An oil of gladneſs, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 45. A fomenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to mitigate aches and torments in the bones, and in the heart.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And can the <hi>Fruits</hi> chuſe but be anſwerable to the <hi>Root?</hi> they muſt needs partake of it. Firſt, becauſe all that we do to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God muſt be done with gladneſs, willingly, and chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: elſe it comes not from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſons, but either from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of bondage, or rather from the Spirit of the world. The new Diſciples received the word <hi>gladly,</hi> and were baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. They continued with one accord daily in the Temple <hi>with gladneſs, and ſimplicity of heart,</hi> Verſe 46. <hi>I was glad when they ſaid unto me,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135920:53"/>
we will go into the houſe of the Lord,</hi> Pſalm 122.1. <hi>Sing Pſalms, make a joyful noiſe unto God, Pſalm</hi> 66.1. Let us come with aſſurance in our ſupplications that we ſhall be heard, praying with Faith in the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Jud. verſe</hi> 20. And then the prayer of the upright ſhall be Gods delight, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. and why God's delight, but becauſe his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants delight in prayer? <hi>He that ſheweth mercy, let him do it with chearfulneſs, Rom.</hi> 12.8. And he that giveth, offereth a blemiſht ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, if he do it grudgingly: <hi>For God loveth a chearful giver,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. Not ſo much but our loſſes and tribulations muſt be ſuſtained with gladneſs. <hi>Thy rod and thy staff do comfort me, Pſalm</hi> 23.4. Enter into the combat willingly, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance will be a pleaſure. Our conſolation aboundeth by Chriſt: for <hi>as ye are partakers of the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135920:53"/>
ſo ſhall ye be alſo of the conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7. Therefore the Apoſtles did change the name of a famous Diſciple, called <hi>Joſes,</hi> into a notion of this Theme, and called him <hi>Barnabas,</hi> which is being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, <hi>The ſon of conſolation, Acts</hi> 4.36. The Rabbies of the <hi>Jews</hi> hold themſelves very cloſe to this doctrine, and would have it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that the merrier the heart is in the Lord, the more capable it is of the Spirit of God. Partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Miriam,</hi> when ſhe propheſied of the mighty acts of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> took a Timbrel in her hand and danced, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20. Partly becauſe that <hi>Samuel,</hi> after he had anointed <hi>Saul</hi> to be King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> told <hi>Saul, Thou ſhalt meet a company of Prophets coming down from the high place, with a Pſaltery, a Tabret, a Pipe, and a Harp; and they ſhall propheſie, and the Spirit of the Lord will come upon
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135920:54"/>
thee, and thou ſhalt propheſie with them, and ſhalt be turned into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. <hi>verſes</hi> 5, 6. More emphatically, when <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> called for <hi>Eliſha</hi> to enquire of the Lord, ſays <hi>Eliſha, Bring me a Minſtrel, and it came to paſs when the Minſtrel played, that the hand of the Lord came upon him,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.15. That by the raviſhing ſtrains of Muſick his mind might be exalted into Heavenly contemplations. Which is a great check to that drowſie dulneſs in devotion, which our late Reformers have brought in, and have excluded the ſolemn melody of the Organ, and the rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of warbling and ſweet voices out of Cathedral Quires. They that miſs that harmony, can beſt tell, how it was wont to raiſe up their Spirit, and as it were to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it out of them to the Quire in Heaven. And beſide, chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135920:54"/>
is not only an adjunct, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion with all the works of grace, in that time they are bringing forth: but being done and finiſht, that which is <hi>poſt-nate,</hi> the after-birth, as I may call it, comes with ſuch a gleam gliding over all the Soul, with ſuch ſerenity and peace of mind as cannot be expreſt; our Conſcience bearing us witneſs that we have been converſant in doing the pleaſure of the Lord, as it is 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>For our rejoycing is this, the teſtimony of our Conſcience, that in ſimplicity, and Godly ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we have had our converſation in the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I ſhall find work to heal the broken in heart, who look upon the fruits of their lives with no content in themſelves, but are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolaced, and caſt down, becauſe neither in number, nor in weight
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135920:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
have they brought in that which the Lord required: they look on their ways, and they find them crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: they look on their heart, and they find it is not conſtant to good purpoſes. To whom I rejoyn; If this proceed from penitence, from quick ſenſe of ſin, from hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which is oppoſite to a ſelf-juſtifying, they have cauſe to praiſe God, that they are thus affected. Let them look narrowly if this Gold (for it may prove no worſe) be currant, when it is brought to the touch-ſtone; then they may lift up their eyes, and look chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully towards Chriſt; for it is no flattery to ſay, they are under his grace and mercy. Deal clearly, that you are aſtoniſht at your frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, becauſe you think you can never work enough, never ſhun ſin enough; and though your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience condemn you, God will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135920:55"/>
you equity againſt the rigour of Conſcience: for he that ſearcheth the heart, <hi>knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 8.22. We are conceived in ſin, and it is ſo inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate unto us, that we have no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be ſo ſpiritualized in this life, that we ſhall not often treſpaſs. <hi>God hath concluded</hi> all in ſin, <hi>all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all, Rom.</hi> 11.32. But it is one thing to fall into ſin, another thing to run into it. One thing to be carried away by the paſſions of it, another to covet, and deſire it. One thing to be overtaken in a fault, another thing to abide in it without repentance. And great odds between thoſe that are given over to pleaſe themſelves in filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and between them that labour and deſire to pleaſe God, though many times they attain not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that willingneſs. The ſcope
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135920:56"/>
of the Seventh Chapter to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> as I apprehend the mind of the Apoſtle, is, to refreſh our guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Conſciences, that a regenerate man is not obnoxious to condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though his fleſh upon ſome temptations make him the ſervant of ſin, becauſe ſtill in his mind he ſerves the law of God. And I am confirm'd in that ſenſe, becauſe without all contradiction He teacheth the like doctrine, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>The fleſh and the Spirit are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary one to another, ſo that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do the things that we would.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And will the righteous God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more of a ſick and feeble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant than his beſt endeavour? Will not Chriſt accept from us the ſame that he did from <hi>Mary,</hi> that broke the Box of Ointment over his head; <hi>She hath done what ſhe could? Mark</hi> 14.8. Let a contrite heart,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135920:56"/>
that would fain be righteous, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the prayer of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Chap. 1. verſe 10. <hi>Let thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy ſervants, who deſire to fear thy name:</hi> or the proteſtation of St. <hi>Paul, Heb.</hi> 13.18. <hi>We truſt we have a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in all things, willing to live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly.</hi> But this deſire and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs muſt be without hypocriſie; not like iron that is gilded, baſe mettal within, and rich without: It muſt be ſteddy, induſtrious, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to perform. Vehement holy deſire is a great degree to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our ſtate. For <hi>the beginning of wiſdom is the deſire of diſcipline, Wiſd.</hi> 6.18. but a lazy careleſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is a great token of imperfection. <hi>The Soul of the ſluggard deſireth, and hath nothing, Prov.</hi> 13.4. And again, <hi>The deſire of the ſlothful kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him, for his hands refuſe to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, Prov.</hi> 21.25. Like Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:135920:57"/>
that when an Officer catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, will feign that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a ſervice, and to be ſet at work: but take them at their word, and they will run away, that they may live in loitering, and upon other mens labours. St. <hi>Paul</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking both rich and poor to libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, according to their reſpective abilities, frames a rule upon that occaſion, which is applicable to all good works, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. <hi>If there be a willing mind, it is accepted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which a man hath, and not according to that which he hath not.</hi> Yea, in ſome caſes, when I deſire a good thing I am at my furtheſt. I deſire the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> at the great day. Come Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> come quickly. I can do no more. I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt. I muſt do no more: for I muſt not attempt my own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135920:57"/>
I wiſh for the converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Jews</hi> to the Faith, I muſt not compel them. This holds in a few things. In the moſt, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs muſt ſhew ſome practice; as in the ſame Chapter, Verſe 11. <hi>Now therefore perform the doing of it: that as there was a readineſs to will, ſo there may be a performance alſo of that which you have.</hi> But to deſire to do, and to do little, is a ſign that there was little deſire. This hath overthrown many, that they deſire not to reach high. But we know that God gives his Grace by Talents, and not in petty ſumms; yet a luke-warm profeſſor can be content with mites. Could ſuch a one get a moderate competency of righteouſneſs, knowing that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſs no man ſhall ſee God, then he would ſit down, and let others ſtrive, if they like it, to be the talleſt Cedars in the houſe of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:135920:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>There are many ſuch indifferent Diſciples, that would be always babes, and never come to a manly growth: wrap themſelves about with as many fig-leaves as would cover their ſhame, and think they want no more apparel. Theſe if they knew what it were to a dram, that would ſerve them to attain ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, they would reach ſo far if the grace of God would aſſiſt them; but would put themſelves to no trouble to purifie their body and Spirit any further. Heres a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a deſire to ſerve God, but with ſo much lazineſs, with ſo much lethargy, that the Lord diſdains it as dead carion. He would ſerve God, and he would ſerve Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. He approves much prayer, but he cannot attend it. He would not for all the world but be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: yet a ſmall ſhare in profit,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135920:58"/>
or a ſnap at a little pleaſure will pervert him to be a diſhoneſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. But real and holy deſire ſtands up for much, though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do ſo much honour to God as he would: like the diſeaſe <hi>Ephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altes,</hi> that oppreſſeth us in the night between ſleeping and waking, we would turn to the other ſide of the bed, and cannot. But to ſhake off this <hi>Incubus,</hi> it liſtens after all the noble exploits that the Saints of God have done, and would exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow them; or, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, run before them: if not, it will be heartily ſorry that frailty makes it come ſhort of the beſt. It would compound for no leſs than to pay all, if it were able. Then you ſhall find the heart pant often with theſe inward earnings; <q>Sweet Saviour, ſhould any of thy ſervants love thee better than I? ſhould any of thy Diſciples be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135920:59"/>
more obedient than I? No Lord: for none of thine are ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to thy paſſion, becauſe none had ſo many ſins to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given. How amiable are thy Commandments O Lord of hoſts? my Soul thirſteth to be the neareſt of them that ſhall ſtand before the preſence of the living God. Lord let me love thee as <hi>Peter</hi> did, Lord let me love thee more than theſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>So I have revealed the Firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts flowing from the Holy Ghoſt by his Inhabitation, and inward Teſtimony: and the next Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts by the Fruits of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and thoſe ſincere deſires of Godlineſs, which by Chriſts mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful interpretation ſupply our fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. All which I conclude out of our Church-Song made to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:135920:59"/>
                  <l>Viſit our minds, and into us</l>
                  <l>Thy Heavenly Grace inſpire,</l>
                  <l>That in all Truth and Godlineſs</l>
                  <l>We may have true deſire.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:135920:60"/>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:135920:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV. Prayer</hi> is the great Inſtrument of a Chriſtian's Comfort. Concerning <hi>Prayer</hi> three things to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>I.</hi> The Subſtance or Matter of Prayer, in three Heads. <hi>1.</hi> Thanksgivings. <hi>2.</hi> Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>3.</hi> Interceſſions. <hi>II.</hi> The Qualification of them that Pray. <hi>III.</hi> The fitneſs of Time for Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</head>
               <p>THE order laid down in the beginning carries me to the Fourth part of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Conſolation, The Heavenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of <hi>Prayer.</hi> It is the lively ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>Faith,</hi> the Embaſſador which <hi>Hope</hi> ſends to God, the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:135920:61"/>
comfort of Love, the fellowſhip of the Spirit, our Advocate unto our Advocate Chriſt <hi>Jeſus:</hi> our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, whoſe ſmoke aſcends up, and is ſweet in the noſtrils of the moſt High: which promiſeth ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſucceſs, that humility had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceive than utter it, leſt we ſhould ſeem to boaſt. A lowly ſupplicant to God never roſe up from his knees, without ſome ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of gracious expectation, nor without a prophetical inſtinct that the mercy of the Lord was nigh at hand. Which fortunate preſage <hi>Iſaiah</hi> confirms unto us, Chap. 56.7. <hi>I will make them joyful in my houſe of Prayer.</hi> And how readily may we uſe this mighty Ordinance of God? how ſoon it may be done, if we have a mind to it? What freedom have we (no man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it) to utter a brief Prayer (and very often if we will) in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:135920:61"/>
toil and buſineſs? <hi>The tongue of the stammerer ſhall be ready to ſpeak elegantly, Iſa.</hi> 32.4. It is ſo facile a part of Religion, as he that hath a tongue can ſcarce miſs it. It is as eaſie to ſay <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> as to ſee Heaven which is always in our eye. Every Sect of Pagans and Idolaters were taught by inſtinct to fly unto it <hi>ex tempore:</hi> as the Heathen Mariners cried every man to his God, <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.5. An Atheiſt falling into a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den danger, as ſuppoſe a Piſtol were put to his breaſt, would cry out as ſoon to God to help him, as any true believer. And he that upon deliberation did ſay there was no God, will break out into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, before he is aware, that there is a God, by natural impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. A poor Whelp hath found a way to lick its own ſores whole with its tongue: ſo when we are
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135920:62"/>
oppreſt with miſery, whether the evil of ſin, or the evil of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we are prompted by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural notions of our Soul to lick the ſore with our tongue, that is, to call for help from Heaven. That Soul, which God did breath into man, cannot ſhake off this principle, That all ſuccour comes from above, for which it muſt breath out it ſelf unto God. No creature among Beaſts, but, being ſmitten, will fall upon the way to relieve it ſelf, except a blind in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitant ſinner. Such as have written upon their ſagacity in that kind, tell us, That the Fiſhes in the freſh waters being ſtruck with a tool of Iron, will rub themſelves upon the glutinous skin of the Tench to be cured. The Hart wounded with an Arrow runs to the Herb <hi>Dittany</hi> to bite it, that the ſhaft may fall out, that ſtruck in his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:135920:62"/>
body. The Swallow will ſeek out the green Tetterwort, to recover the eyes of her young ones, when they are blinded. Only a ſtupid ſinner forgets how to redintegrate his miſerable eſtate, by throwing himſelf down proſtrate before God in humble petition. He walks for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn, loſt to himſelf, loſt to his right wits, becauſe he hath no knowledge, or no good opinion of the comfort of <hi>Prayer.</hi> Which is my purpoſe to make him learn by that which follows, looking upon <hi>the Subſtance</hi> or <hi>Matter of Prayer, The Qualification of him that Prayeth,</hi> and the <hi>fitneſs of Time when Prayer is to be made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. The <hi>Matter of Prayer</hi> is as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious as all occaſions that can be named: it ſhall ſuffice for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to treat of three Heads, <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications with Thanksgivings, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications,</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:135920:63"/>
and <hi>Interceſſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is bent to magnifie the Almighty, to extol his Name, to praiſe him for his Goodneſs. This is the <hi>Hallelujah</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and of the Saints in Heaven, that is, give glory to <hi>Jah,</hi> or the great <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah:</hi> which is followed with a rare variety in the Song of the three Children; <hi>O all ye works of the Lord, bleſs ye the Lord, praiſe him, and magnifie him for ever.</hi> It is a ditty that is balſamed all over with a perfuſion of delight, to praiſe God from all things that he hath made, from the centre of the Earth to the top of Heaven. And this is moſt divinely expreſt in that which is called St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his Hymn in our Common-Prayer; <hi>We praiſe thee, O God, we knowledge thee to be the Lord</hi> — And let the ſervant of God that will liſten to me repeat it often
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135920:63"/>
and often. For it is a piece of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion ſo ſweetly ſpread out into the branches of Heavenly praiſe, Confeſſion of Faith, and devout Petitions, that the like did never come forth, ſince the time it was penn'd. Let me ſpeak to others out of the ſenſe of my own heart, and I may ſafely profeſs, that in the ſervice and worſhip of God, I find nothing ſo delightful, as to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the praiſe and honour of the Lord. If another contradict it, and ſay, that there are ſome means more aptly calculated, as I may ſpeak, for the high Meridian of Comfort; He is He, and I am I, and I appeal from him to my ſelf, what I find in my own motions, and feelings. And what man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the Spirit of a man, which is in him? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. And I obſerve that in the prudent inſtitution of our Church,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135920:64"/>
to hold forth the Conſolation we have in Chriſt, after the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of his Body and Bloud in the bleſſed Sacrament, it teacheth us to break out all together into a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee, <hi>Glory be to God on high — We praiſe thee, we bleſs thee, we glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thee,</hi> &amp;c. For when we are full of that holy Feaſt, and have eaten Angels food, we fall into the tune of Angels, and ſignifie imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before we depart, how much our Spirit rejoyceth in God our Saviour.</p>
               <p>But who knew better the mind of the Lord, than the Spirit it ſelf in thoſe admirable exſtacies of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid? Sing praiſes unto God: for it is pleaſant,</hi> Pſalm 135.3. <hi>Sing praiſes unto our God: for it is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and praiſe is comely,</hi> Pſalm 147.1. <hi>Sing aloud unto God our strength: make a joyful noiſe unto
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:135920:64"/>
the God of Jacob,</hi> Pſalm 81.1. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry furrow in the book of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> is ſown with ſuch ſeeds. I know nothing more certain, more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to expel the ſadneſs of the world, than to ſound out the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Lord as with a Trumpet: and when the heart is caſt down, it will make it rebound from Earth to Heaven. This was the wiſdom of the holy Church throughout all the world (till diſtempers put us out of the right way not long ſince) to ſolemnize the praiſe of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour upon the Feaſts of <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Eaſter,</hi> &amp;c. that we might celebrate the great works which God hath done for us, with the voice of joy, and praiſe, and with a multitude that kept Holy Day, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 42.4. O give thanks unto the Lord, be telling of his mercy and ſalvation from day to day: Give thanks unto him with chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135920:65"/>
for a joyful and pleaſant thing it is to be thankful. Who is a juſt man, and fair condition'd, that would not pay a debt, and be exonerated of it? He that can ſay he hath paid what he ow'd, is it not a quietneſs to his mind to be diſcharg'd?</p>
               <p>It goes further a great deal, and brings more advantage, when we offer up the ſacrifice of retribution, the incenſe of <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> unto the Lord; for we draw on more benefits, when we declare the goodneſs of the Lord upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the old. And the <hi>gratui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> which God gives, is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand fold greater than the preſent which we bring. This propoſed to them that will fly high from the pinacle of the Lord's Prayer, the firſt Petition, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:135920:65"/>2. Neither let them faint that ſtoop low in <hi>Supplication:</hi> for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will embrace them on every ſide.</p>
               <p>Two things being put together are of much weight: we pray with God's Spirit, and by his Word. He invites us in his Word to pray: and he gives the gift with which we pray. <hi>I will pour upon the houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>the Spirit of Grace and Supplications, Zach.</hi> 12.10. Did He pour upon us his Grace? and have we received a Commandment, the outward ſign of his Will? and can we ſuſpect af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, that He will put us off, and deny us? Is his Grace given in vain? or hath He ſent his Word to delude us? He hath kindled a fire in our breaſts, and it is an Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:135920:66"/>
flame that burns within us.
<q>Lord, though we are vile and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable, thou canſt not deſpiſe the acting of thine own Spirit, nor fruſtrate thine own operations.</q> Or do we come unbidden when we caſt our ſelves down in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? <q>Nay Lord, thou haſt beckned, and called us, Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden.</q> Hold faſt to theſe two, and who can forbid us to be comforted? the Lord bids us pray, and he gives us a heart to pray. For it is not ſtrange to his mercy (perhaps it is ſtrange to mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt) to give us ſtrength to bring forth that obedience, both to will and to do, which himſelf hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. As he gave the Bleſſed Virgin ſtrength to bring forth the Babe, who was conceived, and formed in her womb by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:135920:66"/>This I do the rather enforce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we can ſee no comfort in our ſelves: therefore as I derive all the vertue and ſpirituality that is in Prayer from the efficacy of Grace. So I refer all the ſucceſs to Chriſt, in whom we are bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſſings, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye ask the Father in my Name, he will give it, Jo.</hi> 15.16. But He and his Father are one, therefore he ſays, <hi>If ye ſhall ask the Father any thing in my Name, I will do it, Jo.</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> 14. If we had no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter means to God than our ſelves, and our own merits, there were no hope to ſpeed: nay our hearts would be as faint and dead, as if we heard our ſelves denied before we had opened our lips. But we conclude, as it is to the moſt of our Collects, <hi>through Chriſt our Lord.</hi> When we bring that Name in the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135920:67"/>
rear, and quote him for our Merit and Mediator, then I know it will be well, and that the Lord will hear the petitions of his ſervants. Should we not put our requeſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſts hand to offer them to his Father, <hi>Sion</hi> might ſpread forth her complaints, and there would be none to comfort her: and we might remain for ever in that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy plight, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 77. <hi>verſe</hi> 3. <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred God, and was troubled: I complained, and my Spirit was overwhelmed.</hi> But if we renounce our wretched ſelves, and imagine not the leaſt intrinſecal perfection to be in our Prayers, do we ſail then by the Cape of Good Hope? yes, becauſe God is contented to yield upon ſuch addreſſes. <hi>Jacob</hi> may wreſtle with the Angel all night, and proteſt he will not let him go till he have bleſſed him. But <hi>Victus eſt quia voluit:</hi> God was
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135920:67"/>
overcome, becauſe he would be overcome of <hi>Jacob:</hi> he lets us pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, becauſe he is willing to yield: but there is no ſtrength is us to win, if he would not ſuffer himſelf to be vanquiſht.</p>
               <p>There is no other perſon but Chriſt, in whom the Father (I know not what kind of neceſſity to call it) cannot but be well pleaſed. Which made him ſay before his Diſciples, <hi>Jo.</hi> 11.41. <hi>Father, I thank thee that thou haſt heard me, and I know that thou heareſt me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways:</hi> As it is alſo, Heb. 5.7. <hi>Who in the days of his fleſh, when he had offered up Prayers and Supplications, with strong crying and tears, was heard for his piety.</hi> This is the preheminence of our High Prieſt, who is an Orator for us all, that the Lord cannot reject his Prayers. Therefore committing our daily
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:135920:68"/>
Oraiſons to our High Prieſt, to bear them into the Holy of Holies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Father, they are in a ſure hand: and they that know his Name will put their truſt in thee, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 9.10. Much more they that know his Office perfectly. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let Prayer carry on theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations with it; That we are invited by God to that duty: That the Spirit inſtigates us unto it, and helps our infirmities, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. That it is preſented to the Father by the mediation of the Son; then how canſt thou be ſad, O my Soul, and fear to miſcarry? Is not the lot fallen unto thee in a pleaſant field? and may'ſt thou not promiſe to thy ſelf a very goodly heritage?</p>
               <p>Without all diſpute then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed unto <hi>Prayer,</hi> and for a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, 1. Ask in Faith, <hi>James</hi> 1.6. that is, attribute unto God that he
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135920:68"/>
is Almighty, and can do above all that we ask, or think: Conſent to his truth, that he is faithful in his promiſes: for he that believeth not thoſe, makes God a lyar. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his goodneſs and mercy through Chriſt, that He will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold no good thing from them that lead a Godly life. Let there be no wavering, no diſputing about theſe Attributes of God, leſt we be condemned out of our own mouth. So much Faith, ſo much efficacy, ſo much confidence, ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in Prayer.</p>
               <p>Then will a ſolicitous Chriſtian reply, What will become of me? I have not that plenitude of Faith: at leaſt in ſundry occaſions I have it not to aſcertain my ſelf that I ſhall prevail with God. No more had <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf a perfect Faith without any flaw. Excellent things
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135920:69"/>
are ſpoken of him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Who againſt hope believed in hope:</hi> and <hi>that he staggered not at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, but was strong in Faith,</hi> Verſe 20. Yet ſee how he ſtoopt a little, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.18. <hi>Shall a Son be born un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that is an hundred years old? and ſhall</hi> Sarah <hi>that is ninety years old, bear! O that</hi> Iſhmael <hi>may live?</hi> God is not extream to mark what is done amiſs in every convulſion of Faith: which appears, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 31. <hi>verſe</hi> 22. <hi>I ſaid in my haſte, I am caſt out of thine eyes: nevertheleſs thou heardeſt the voice of my ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when I cried unto thee.</hi> You muſt be ſure that in general <hi>David</hi> ſubſcribed to the power, and truth, and goodneſs of God: but there was a temptation upon him at that time in ſome particular caſe, in which he diſtruſted, or doubted that there was no likelihood to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail. But if there be ſuch a one
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135920:69"/>
that ſays, I will pray, but I know I ſhall be never the better, he is an infidel, and mocks God: in that bad mind he did well to ſay he ſhould be never the better: for he did uſurp a form of Godlineſs, and denied the power thereof.</p>
               <p>He is the right Supplicant, but a very rare one, that hath no ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or diffidence in his heart, that comes cloſe up to our Saviour's rule, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.24. <hi>What things ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye deſire when ye Pray, believe that ye receive them, and ye ſhall have them.</hi> Yet the Lord will not caſt them off, who are but in the next form, and do not reſolutely promiſe ſucceſs unto themſelves in the inſtant of their preſent Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations: but bear it thus between Faith and doubting, whether I ſhall ſucceed in this or that I am not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, but of this I am moſt aſſured,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:135920:70"/>
that I ſhall be the better for my Prayers. And I would it were thus and thus, becauſe I conceive it would be beſt for me: but I am certain it will be better than the beſt that I can imagine, which the Lord knows to be moſt expedient.</p>
               <p>Another perhaps may wrangle himſelf into an error, and ſay, How do the Heathen and the wicked obtain good things, if nothing will prevail with God but the Prayer of Faith? Conſider that even a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan and Idolater would ever Pray, but that they have ſome kind of belief to obtain fruit by their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. The King of <hi>Nineveh</hi> bad a ſolemn Faſt at the hearing of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah's</hi> propheſie; <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Who can tell if God will turn, and repent, and turn away from his fierce anger, that we periſh not? Jon.</hi> 3.9. None but a Lunatick would ask for relief
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135920:70"/>
from them, that had neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his caſe, nor power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs it. O but the prayers of ſuch are not grounded on the Faith that we ſpeak of. It is true: ſuch a Faith as poſſeſt Idolaters, is not that which impetrates mercy from God. Then I ſay, neither <hi>Jews,</hi> nor <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> nor wicked men get any thing by that Prayer, to which the promiſe is made, <hi>Ask, and ye ſhall have.</hi> For whether they Pray or not, all that they obtain had come to paſs, though they had held their peace. It is for our ſins, and to ſcourge us, that they have kingdoms, and victories, it is not their motley-faith that did purchaſe them. And for all manner of ſtore and plenty that the Earth yields to them, it is but as God gives fod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Cattle, and meat to the yong Ravens that call upon him.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:135920:71"/>2. The Prayer of <hi>Faith</hi> then is only available: but out of the mouth of an <hi>humble</hi> ſuiter. For who will give an alms to a proud begger? <hi>Thus ſaith the high and lofty one, that inhabiteth Eternity, I dwell with him that is of a contrite and humble Spirit, to revive the Spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones, Iſa.</hi> 57.15. Let the compariſon between the <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> and the <hi>Phariſee</hi> remain for ever in our memory, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. The Prayer of the poor deſtitute, the contrite, the penitent, the bleeding heart is a ſacrifice well ſeaſon'd with the ſalt of anguiſh and miſery. Away with high looks, and high words. <hi>Lord, thou doſt hear the deſire of the humble, and doſt prepare their heart,</hi> Pſalm 10.17. And <hi>God comforteth thoſe that are caſt down,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6. Put your
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:135920:71"/>
ſelf back, who are but duſt and aſhes in a great diſtance from the Lord, that you may behold him the better in his infinite greatneſs. And a lowly heart will never ſpare to deject the body. <hi>O come let us worſhip and fall down, and kneel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord our Maker. Solomon</hi> pray'd upon his knees, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. ſo did <hi>Daniel,</hi> Chap. 6. ſo did <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> when meſſengers came to him from <hi>Cornelius, Acts</hi> 9. ſo St. <hi>Paul: For this cauſe I bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jeſus, Eph.</hi> 3.14. And not only men upon Earth, but the glorious Spirits in Heaven, caſt themſelves and their Crowns down before him that ſitteth on the Throne, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. Nay the Son of God fell down upon his knees, and pray'd unto his Father, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.41.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Faſting,</hi> which is a pregnant
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:135920:72"/>
circumſtance of <hi>humiliation,</hi> was much in uſe with Prayer; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are innumerous: to ſignifie we had no part in any comfort, nor any delight in the Creatures, till we were reconciled to the Lord. So was <hi>Sackcloth</hi> uſed; and all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel of beauty, all ornaments of riches and pride were put off for that time. Let them be no more than outward circumſtances; yet they are ſignificant.</p>
               <p>But that which is a ſure compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and moſt intimate to <hi>humility</hi> in Prayer, is <hi>Patience.</hi> It breaks not away in a pet, becauſe it is not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd at the firſt or ſecond asking: that's diſdainful and arrogant. It holds on, and attends, and cries till the throat is dry: <hi>I waited pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for the Lord, Pſalm</hi> 40.1. And there muſt be patient continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in them that ſeek for Glory
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:135920:72"/>
and Immortality, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Faith</hi> is the <hi>foundation</hi> of Prayer: and, to continue the Metaphor, <hi>Patience</hi> is the Roof. The winds blow: look to the foundation, or the building will fall. Rain and ſtorms will deſcend: but if they light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Roof that is cloſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, they run aſide, and are caſt upon the ground. He that expects God's pleaſure from day to day, will neither faint, nor fret, that his ſuit hangs long in the Court of Requeſts: ſuch ſtorms as proceed from murmuring, cannot beat through a ſolid Roof. Says <hi>Hab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bak.</hi> Chap. 2. Verſe 3. A great thing will the Lord bring to paſs, but not preſently ſays the Lord: <hi>The Viſion is yet for an appointed time, but at the end it ſhall ſpeak, and not lye: though it tarry, wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come.</hi> Many diſeaſes will never be cured well,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:135920:73"/>
unleſs they be long a curing: and many deliverances will never be throughly ſetled, unleſs they be long a preparing: and many mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are hid like ſeed in the ground, and will be long a growing.</p>
               <p>I give God thanks that every bleſſing of worldly Comfort that I Pray'd for, the longer I was kept from it, and the more I pray'd for it, I found it the greater in the end.</p>
               <p>Obſerve that there is nothing of moment, yea be it of leſſer and vulgar ſize, with which the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God hath not interwoven a thouſand things to be diſpatcht with it, which requires time, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſeven years to finiſh them. Expect therefore from the Divine wiſdom to do all things in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: and give honour to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Majeſty to wait his leiſure.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:135920:73"/>
                  <hi>For yet a little, and he, that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry,</hi> Heb. 10.37.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third thing which gives aſſurance of Comfort to <hi>Prayer</hi> is <hi>Zeal, Devotion, Fervency,</hi> which will pluck on <hi>Patience</hi> further and further. For he that is <hi>zealous</hi> in any thing will not eaſily give over, till he have brought his ends to paſs. <hi>Zeal</hi> is a continual and an earneſt ſupplicant, it Prays <hi>without ceaſing,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. Prays <hi>exceedingly,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10. Asks with confidence, ſeeks with diligence, knocks with perſeverance. A ſwarm of Bees, that is, many thouſands muſt gather into a Hive to fill it with Hony-combs: and a ſwarm of Prayers is ſweeter before the Lord than the Hony, and the Hony-comb. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is as vehement as it is aſſidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>labouring fervently for you in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:135920:74"/>
Prayers, Coloſſ.</hi> 4.12. Stir up your wit, and diligence, and memory, and meditations, when you come to ſpread out your wants before your Father: but if you yawn out heedleſs, heartleſs petitions, you ſhall depart with diſcouragement, as it is <hi>Pſalm</hi> 80.4. <hi>O Lord God of hoſts, how long wilt thou be angry with the Prayer of thy people?</hi> The <hi>Laodiceans</hi> were lukewarm, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hot nor cold in the worſhip of God: therefore the Spirit ſaid to the Angel of that Church, <hi>Be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and repent, Revel.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Zeal</hi> is defined to be <hi>a vehement and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed love.</hi> There muſt be an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and a flame in Prayer, as if we would mount it up like fire to Heaven. Then we may ſay that a <hi>Seraphin</hi> hath laid a coal from the Altar upon our mouth, and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our lips, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Zeal</hi> takes away the Soul for a time, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:135920:74"/>
it far above us. I write to them that have felt it, that it darts a mans Spirit out of him like an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out of a bow. This is it which infallibly begets Hope, Comfort, Patience, all in a Sheaf, as they are divinely put together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>verſes</hi> 11, 12. <hi>Fervent in Spirit, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lord, rejoycing in Hope, patient in Tribulation, continuing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The tranſportment of Zeal will excuſe, or rather commend ſome Ejaculations of Prayer, which ſeem to be too bold with God; as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 44. <hi>How long wilt thou turn away the face from us O Lord? and forgetteſt our miſery and trouble:</hi> So Jer. 14.9. <hi>Why ſhould'ſt thou be as a man aſleep? and as a mighty man that cannot ſave us?</hi> And we do but follow our Saviour's pattern in it upon the Croſs, <hi>My God, my God,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:135920:75"/>
why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Tell not a troubled heart that is in anguiſh, tell it not of modeſty: it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement it will not be tied to. The <hi>Shunamite</hi> ſwallowed up in ſorrow for the loſs of her child, runs to mount <hi>Carmel</hi> to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and before ſhe ſaid any thing, ſhe catcht him faſt by the feet: <hi>Gehazi</hi> thought it irreverent and unwoman-like beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and laid hold to thruſt her away: <hi>Let her alone,</hi> ſays the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>for her Soul is vexed within her,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.27. The paſſions of an afflicted Soul have much indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to break out far. They are not in good compaſs, till vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Zeal carry them beyond or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary rule and faſhion. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> did more than this, the firſt time ſhe came to our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37. ſhe came into a ſtrange houſe without leave and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: into the houſe of a <hi>Phariſee,</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:135920:75"/>
and thoſe hypocrites would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuſpected ſinners: ſhe takes op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to come at dinner-time, being a gueſt unbidden: ſhe gives no ſalutation to the company, but falls down at our Saviours feet, and lays her kiſſes thick upon them: ſays a holy writer to it, it is <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Great, <hi>Haſt thou no fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, woman? hath modeſty quite leſt thee?</hi> And he anſwers himſelf, <hi>Minimè, pudor intus erat.</hi> That which ſhe was aſham'd of was within her, ſhe was ſo aſhamed of her ſins, that ſhe forgat all other ſhamefac'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. You ſee that Zeal will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don boldneſs, and will give autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to prayer to expoſtulate with God, and hath a toleration, as it were, to quarrel with his mercy.</p>
               <p>Now a Chriſtian, ſenſible of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny imperfections, will cry out, O that I could attain to ſome degrees
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135920:76"/>
of Zeal! I am no <hi>Shunamite,</hi> no <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> no <hi>Paul</hi> fervent in Spirit. I am carried away with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, when I ſpeak unto the Lord in Prayer; and through the multitude of various thoughts I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what I am about. O Chriſt help our frailties, and keep our minds fixed upon thee, when we ask any thing in thy Name. One body cannot be in two places at once: and one heart cannot be in Heaven and Earth together. O let us cover our faces with the wings of the Cherubims, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.2. that we may not ſee enticements to diſtract us. Watch, and Pray: watch this wandring heart, that it may not be ſtoln away by fancies, that move in our mind continually, like motes in the beams of the Sun. Defie Satan, and bid him abandon. As they that have committed a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery run away from a Hue and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:135920:76"/>
Cry: ſo the Devil will run away from the noiſe of your Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when you challenge him for ſacriledge, that he hath robb'd you of your Devotion.</p>
               <p>To do more yet, I will aſſay to preſcribe a remedy to a diſeaſe, I fear, not quite to be cur'd. But firſt feel your own pulſe, and your fitneſs for the Heavenly work of <hi>Prayer</hi> before you begin it. See that you be not drowzy and ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: for a ſluggard will be incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with various and recurrent thoughts. Neither would I have you to protract Prayer to that length, which otherwiſe you would have done, when your mind and devotion fail you. Short and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Prayers, <hi>Collects</hi> well fill'd with words and matter, and not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted till they may be cenſur'd for babbling, are more prevalent
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:135920:77"/>
with God, when Zeal doth manage them, than to ſpend out time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a fervent and well fixt intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Prayers of the great Saints in Scripture are compendious, they are ſtrong in ſenſe, and ſpeak home. A roſe is ſweeter in the bud, than in the blown flower: and what your abate at one time in length to anticipate diſtraction, you may fill up the meaſure when you will by uſing them the oftner. I have known ſome ſervants of God, very circumſpect in their ways, that uſe for the moſt part to read their Prayers either Printed or Written, that ſeeing the matter of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, they might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contain themſelves from all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies. To which end it is preſcribed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though a Prieſt can ſay the Maſs by heart, yet he muſt read it out of his book, to keep the cloſer to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:135920:77"/>
of his duty. But when all is ſaid, happy are they that offend leaſt in this kind: for all offend.</p>
               <p>And who can we blame but our ſelves, that are remiſs, and not half ſo earneſt as we ſhould be to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with God? which I demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate thus: Let there be any thing in our Prayers, which we are more eagerly ſet upon to obtain, than all the reſt, we will never ſtart aſide, nor run out of our circle when we come to that petition. <hi>Animus eſt ubi amat,</hi> The mind is with that, and in that which it loves. If we did long for every member of our Prayer, as much as for that ſpecial thing, which we did ſo eminently deſire, we would continue from the beginning to the end of Prayer with little or no diverſion.</p>
               <p>This bottom is not wound up,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:135920:78"/>
till I give a warning to Zeal, as it is <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.18. <hi>It is good to be zealouſly affected always in a good thing.</hi> Look that your petitions be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled into ſuch things, as the Word and Spirit do appoint, and ſtir you up to ask, and you <hi>ſhall not be aſhamed of your ſacrifice, Hoſ.</hi> 4.19. But if you be frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, the Prophet will tell you again, <hi>Ye have ſown the wind, and ye ſhall reap the whirle-wind, Hoſ.</hi> 8.7. or the Apoſtle tells you plainly, <hi>Ye ask, and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſs, James</hi> 4.3. Ask for the kingdom of Heaven, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of God's glory, for new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life, and obedience to the will of God; ask for pardon of ſins in Chriſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> for grace in the Holy Ghoſt to reſiſt temptations; ask our offended Father for mercy, to be delivered from the wrath which we have deſerved: and let
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:135920:78"/>
the ſeventh part of our Prayer be for the things of this life, and for them with moderation, according to that port and perſon which we bear in the world, and be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the portion allotted to you: aim by this level, and you hit the mark. What mighty bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings did fall upon <hi>Solomon,</hi> becauſe he deſired not the advantages of pomp and luxury, when God put it to him in a dream what to ask? he deſired an underſtanding and a wiſe heart: and the ſpeech pleaſed the Lord, that <hi>Solomon</hi> had asked this thing, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Interceſſions,</hi> that is, Prayers wherein we mediate to God for others, muſt now be thought of, and the Comfort redounding from them. The duty is ſtrictly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to Pray for one another, <hi>James</hi> 5.16. And, <hi>I will that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:135920:79"/>
be made for all men, for Kings and all that are in Authority,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. when we do ſo, we have done what we are bidden: and having done that, albeit we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervants to God, we are not uncomfortable to our ſelves. For it is the firſt part of the reward of a good deed, that we can ſay to our Conſcience we have done it. Beſide, the work of love is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful to the Spirit; and to help others in our Prayers is the largeſt and wideſt work of Charity, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do good to all upon the face of the Earth, and ſtretching forth its hands that the whole world may be the better for the calves of our lips. Chiefly commending the whole ſtate of Chriſts Church to Gods mercy, yet alſo, (as may be ſeen in our Collect uſed on <hi>Good-friday</hi>) not forgetting to remember Chriſt for Jews, Turks, Infidels,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:135920:79"/>
Hereticks, to take from them ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, hardneſs of heart, and contempt of the Word: not only that the Sheep of Chriſts paſture might be bleſt, but that it might be well with <hi>Nero,</hi> and ſuch as he, that were the Lions that devoured us. This is Charity not only to have Communion with all the Saints, but compaſſion for all the world. Therein we follow the foot-ſteps of Chriſt in his mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as far as we are able, who hath an <hi>unchangeable Prieſthood,</hi> and <hi>ever lives to make Interceſſion for us,</hi> Heb. 7.25. And <hi>who bare the ſins of many, and made Interceſſion for the tranſgreſſors,</hi> Iſa. 53.12.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it is the office of thoſe that have great intereſt in God's favour, to bleſs others with their Prayers, as the Lord told <hi>Abimelech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar, Abraham is a Prophet,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:135920:80"/>
and he ſhall pray for thee, and thou ſhalt live, Gen.</hi> 20.7. So he ſaid to <hi>Eliphaz</hi> the <hi>Temanite,</hi> and to his other two friends, <hi>My ſervant</hi> Job <hi>ſhall Pray for you, for him will I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, Job</hi> 42.8. All <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been deſtroyed for worſhipping the Calf in <hi>Horeb,</hi> had not <hi>Moſes</hi> his choſen ſtood before him in the breach, to turn away his wrath, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 106.23. What? ſays an old writer, art thou <hi>Moſes</hi> more merciful than God? art thou more pitiful to the people, than he that ſaves us from all evil? No, ſays he, thou art in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſhort of the loving kindneſs of the Lord; but he put thy Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the proof, to ſee what ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement entreaties thou wouldſt make for the deliverance of the Nation. When the ſame people were like to be overrun by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> what courſe did <hi>Samuel</hi> take? ſays he, <hi>Gather all Iſrael to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:135920:80"/>
Mizpah,</hi> (which was a <hi>Proſeucha,</hi> or place for publick Prayer) <hi>and I will Pray for you to the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 7.5. And you ſhall find moſt victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſucceſs upon it, <hi>Verſe</hi> 10. What comfortable Orators are the mighty Saints of God? what a ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard it is unto us all, when they live among us? A wiſe man is the price and redemption of many fools, ſays a Heathen: ſo a Mediator, that is very dear to God, is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection not only to the good, but to the wicked that are about him. Have we not cauſe then to Pray for the continuance of ſuch, that they may live long to Pray for us? Should <hi>Paul</hi> need to deſire the Prayers of the <hi>Theſſalonians?</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.25. or of the <hi>Hebrews?</hi> Chap. 13.18. Could they forget that, which ſo much concern'd their welfare? Now the worthy ſervants of the Lord may prevail much one by
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:135920:81"/>
one: others of the common rank had need to meet by hundreds, and by thouſands, in great congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that every ſingle mans Prayer may be a drop in a ſhower, that while every man Prays for all, all may Pray for every man. So great is the opinion of good conſequents from the Interceſſion of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that infidels and ungodly, who thought it would be labour in vain to ſpeak to God for themſelves, have ſued unto the Saints on Earth to prefer petitions for them. <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that worſhipt falſe Gods, ſent to the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to Pray for the life of the King and his Sons, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.10. And they that perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Jeremy</hi> beſought him, <hi>Pray for us unto the Lord our God,</hi> Jer. 42.20. And <hi>Simon Magus</hi> turn'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>Peter</hi> and the Apoſtles to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for him, <hi>Pray unto the Lord for me, that none of theſe things
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:135920:81"/>
which you have ſpoken, come upon me, Acts</hi> 8.24. This is the ſumm, that Interceſſion of Prayer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther active or Paſſive, whether it be to give, or to receive a bleſſing, is exceeding full of Conſolation.</p>
               <p n="2">II. To go in order to the next Head, Who they be that ſhall get benefit, and comfort by Prayer, is quickly defined. We know that <hi>all things work together for good to them that love God, Rom.</hi> 8.28. to none other, you may be ſure. He that doth not truly call the God of Heaven his Father, as Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins his Prayer, ſhall have no ſhare in the portion of Sons. We may intercede for prophane and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent men, and our Prayer ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into our own boſom. But while they remain ſuch, the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Lord will be ſtrange un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. They are not of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:135920:82"/>
of the myſtical Church, and all the freſh Springs are derived unto them that are within the Sanctuary. While the <hi>Jews</hi> continued under the hardneſs of their heart, God diſcharged the Prophet for appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their behalf. <hi>Pray not thou for this people, neither lift up cry, nor Prayer for them, neither make Interceſſion to me, for I will not hear thee, Jer.</hi> 7.16. And with no leſs, or rather more ſeverity, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Though theſe three men, Noah, Job and Daniel, were in the land, they ſhould deliver none but their own Souls.</hi> And if the wicked commence a ſuit in their own name, the Lord will not be entreated of them. What have they to do with holy Ordinances, that have no fellowſhip with holy practices? To come before the Lord with a lap full of ſins, and a mouth full of prayers, what an Heterogeneal Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:135920:82"/>
is it? will the Mediator Chriſt <hi>Jeſus</hi> bring it for them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Father? <hi>If I regard iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in my heart, the Lord will not hear me,</hi> Pſalm 66.18. <hi>And the throne of iniquity ſhall have no fellowſhip with thee,</hi> Pſalm 99. verſe 20.</p>
               <p>Many in our land, and in our days Pray for the confuſion of them that brought all to confuſion; but themſelves are in purſuance of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious crimes, and rebellion againſt God. They would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance that government to which we have ſworn to be faithful by the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: but they make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to break their Oaths and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants which they have made to God. It is not to ſuppreſs ſin, and tyranny, and injuſtice, that they are inſtant with God; but to be reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their own injuries and loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:135920:83"/>
Their Prayers are compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch ſins as quite marre them. So many a pair of Beads have been dropt in corners for the extirpation of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Many a Maſs hath been ſaid for the good ſucceſs of Jeſuitical Treaſons. Many a Roſary was run over to bring the <hi>Powder-treaſon</hi> to its bloudy birth. If they have no better ſtuff than this in their Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, they had as good Pray to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils as to Saints. <hi>I will that men Pray always, or every where, lifting up holy hands, without wrath,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. Let go wrath, and malice, and bitterneſs. Holineſs becometh the houſe of Prayer, and holineſs becometh the mouth of Prayer. <hi>If any man be a worſhipper of God, and doth his will, him he heareth, Jo.</hi> 9.31. Do juſtly, live chaſtly, give charitably, walk circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then Pray confidently.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:135920:83"/>
                  <hi>For whatſoever we ask, we receive of him, becauſe we keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and do thoſe things which are pleaſing in his ſight,</hi> 1 Epiſt. Jo. 3.22.</p>
               <p>But then will the trembling Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſay, wo is me, for I am a great ſinner, wo is me, for I am filthy, and polluted, and of unclean lips, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.5. then how ſhall I turn me to my God in Prayer? O thou that falleſt low upon the Earth, oppreſſed with the burden of thy ſins, ſtand up, and be chearful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: none is fit for Prayer in the Militant Church, but ſuch an humble ſinner. God draws thee, and none but thoſe that are like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, near unto his mercy. Though thy ſins do cleave unto thee, be comforted that thou doſt not cleave unto thy ſins. <hi>Elkanah</hi> gave a more worthy portion to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:135920:84"/>
                  <hi>Hannah</hi> that was barren, but meek and devout, than to <hi>Peninnah</hi> that bare him ſons and daughters, but was proud and ſcornful, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.5. God hath heard his beloved Son, when he made Prayers for ſinners, will hear thoſe ſinners that are his Sons, when they ask any thing in the name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Good fruit muſt be brought forth in a good ſeaſon, which only remains to be thought upon, and to be added to the Conſolation of Prayer. <hi>For every thing there is a ſeaſon, and a time to every purpoſe under the Heaven,</hi> Eccleſ. 3.1. But neither days, nor hours, nor ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did ever come amiſs to faithful Prayer. <hi>Evening, and morning, and at Noon will I Pray, and cry aloud, and He ſhall hear my voice, Pſal.</hi> 55.17. which includes all the ſpace of duration. For all time is
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:135920:84"/>
included in <hi>Morning, Noon,</hi> and <hi>Night. Pray without ceaſing,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.17. <hi>Praying always with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit, and watching thereunto with all perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> Epheſ. 6.18. Short paſſes, quick ejections, conciſe forms and remembrances, holy breathings, Prayers like little poſies, may be ſent forth without number on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion, and God will note them in his book.</p>
               <p>But all that have a care to walk with God, fill their veſſels more largely as ſoon as they riſe, before they begin the work of the day, and before they lie down again at night. Which is to obſerve what the Lord appointed in the Levitical miniſtery, a <hi>morning,</hi> and an <hi>even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lamb</hi> to be laid upon the Altar. So with them that are not ſtark ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious, Prayer is the key to open
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:135920:85"/>
the day, and the bolt to ſhut in the night. But as the skies drop the early dew, and the evening dew upon the graſs: yet it would not ſpring and grow green by that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and double falling of the dew, unleſs ſome great ſhowers at certain ſeaſons did ſupply the reſt. So the cuſtomary devotion of Prayer twice a-day is the falling of the early and the latter dew: but if you will increaſe and flouriſh in the works of grace, empty the great clouds ſometimes, and let them fall into a full ſhower of Prayer: chuſe out the ſeaſons in your own diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when Prayer ſhould overflow like <hi>Jordan</hi> in the time of harveſt. keep ſtrictly, as much as you are, able, to thoſe times of the day, which you have deſigned to appear in before the Lord: for then you offer up not only your Prayers, but the ſtrict obſervation of ſet
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:135920:85"/>
times, which is a double ſacrifice, and an evidence that you will not diſpenſe to pretermit that holy work for any a vocation. He that refers himſelf at large to Pray when he is at leiſure, gives God the worſt of the day, that is, his idle time. I account them prudent therefore, that are preciſe in keeping Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical hours of Prayer, as they call them, ſo they Pray to God alone, who alone knows their heart: and ſo they Pray <hi>with the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. that is, in a tongue wherein they know what they ſay, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the language wherein they vent the meditations of their Spirit. This was the milk that the Church of <hi>England</hi> gave every day out of her breaſts, to praiſe God in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer at ſet hours, before noon and after, in the aſſemblies of her devout children. How many
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:135920:86"/>
have rejoyced to hear the Chiming of the Bells to call them together, and would never miſs their ſtation? As <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> went together to the Temple at the hour of Prayer, being the ninth hour, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.1. O when will theſe profane days come to an end, that we may again ſo orderly, ſo delightfully appear before the living God?</p>
               <p>Of one thing the Devil diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed us many years paſt in the time of Prayer, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was the Night-offices of prayers, called <hi>Vigils,</hi> which are diſuſed, becauſe it was feared they grew incident to ſcandal and uncleanneſs. And though they be left off (I believe for good reaſon) in a concourſe of open meeting, yet let not God loſe his tribute of Prayer, which ſhould be paid him in the ſtill and quiet opportunity of the night. The day is God's, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:135920:86"/>
the night is God's, the darkneſs and light to him are both alike: let not ſo many hours, as run out from our lying down to our riſing up again, paſs away without any Prayer. Says <hi>David, O Lord I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred thee in my bed, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated on thee in the night-watches, Pſalm</hi> 63.6. It ſeems, while the Tabernacle of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtood, that the Prieſts did ſome duties in it all night long. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 134.1. <hi>Bleſs the Lord ye ſervants of the Lord, which by night stand in the houſe of the Lord.</hi> The Apoſtles allowed widows muſt continue in Supplication and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers night and day, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.5. And <hi>Anna</hi> the widow-propheteſs ſerved God with Faſting and Prayers <hi>night and day, Luke</hi> 2.37. The Lord hath foretold that he will come as a thief in the night at the great day, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. Therefore, O Lord, with my Soul will I deſire thee in
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:135920:87"/>
the night, and at midnight will I think upon thee, and call unto thee; that if it ſhall be this night, even now, when Chriſt <hi>Jeſus</hi> will come to judge the world, my Soul may find mercy from him, and both Body and Soul may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſo continue with him for ever.</p>
               <p>All this about the opportunity of time ſhall ſhut up with one Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 32.6. <hi>Every one that is Godly ſhall Pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, O Lord, in a time that thou mayeſt be found.</hi> When you find ſtirrings and impulſions more than ordinary to provoke you to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, follow the admonition of the Spirit, and let not ſuch a time ſlip. You know not whether ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine preſage may rowle in your thoughts again. I make no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but there are ſome Critical mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:135920:87"/>
wherein God offers more than he will do again; if you neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect him when he courts you with ſo great advantage. But now change the caſe from mine to the whole Nations, from private to publick, then thus I will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory in my reſolution: There is no time too late for any Chriſtian that lives, in his ſingle perſon, to beſeech God to be merciful to him: he may find the ſame propitiouſneſs that the penitent thief did. But there may be a time too late to ſave a Kingdom, or a ſtate from ruine, when the Lord hath decreed the period of it. Therefore when confuſions threaten and begin to peep out, watch them betimes, and let the whole Land Pray for peace, and let the Governours prepare conditions for it, to avert publick calamitie. If we let tumults and conſpiracies grow to a head, it will
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:135920:88"/>
be in vain to ſtruggle by monthly or weekly humiliations, when our deſtiny is unavoidable. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſays, that a diſcontented perſon challeng'd the Oracle of <hi>Delphos</hi> that it never gave a comfortable anſwer. That's your fault ſays the Oracle, for none of you come to me till your caſe is paſt help. <hi>Venimus huc lapſis quaeſitum oracula rebus,</hi> ſays the Poet, that ever keeps <hi>decorum</hi> in his Verſes. Therefore awake right early: ſeek the Lord in the firſt ſeaſon, that the courſe of miſery may not wax too ſtrong and remedileſs. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Prophet will ſay, <hi>The days of viſitation are come, the days of recompence are come, Iſrael ſhall know it, Hoſ.</hi> 9.7. and then whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ye flie for help to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. But prevent ſuch diſmal tribulations, while it is called To day. For nothing is more Conſolato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than ſeaſonable Supplication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:135920:88"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How the <hi>Sacraments</hi> miniſter to a Chriſtian's Comfort. A general Survey of <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Five Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why God ordained Two <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> under the Goſpel. What Comforts flow from the Grace of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> What Comforts flow from the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough by that which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath been ſet forth, I truſt I may aſſume, that every one, that ſets his heart to make uſe of it, hath drunk well, yet as the Ruler of the Feaſt ſaid at the Marriage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee, I have kept the good,</hi> that is, the beſt, <hi>Wine until now, Jo.</hi> 2.10. The water of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:135920:89"/>
life in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> the wine that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth the Spiritual thirſt in the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> Other things in the Word report unto us what a good land the Lord hath promiſed to his <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but theſe two Sacraments are <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſuah,</hi> ſpies that have ſeen, and ſearcht the land, and bring us ſenſible and ſure ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that it is a noble land, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Milk and Hony: by the Grapes which they have brought with them, and by their ocular and diligent ſurvey, they yield evident teſtimony that God hath provided a gracious Country for us in the Kingdom of Heaven. To put all my work of Conſolation into one proſpect together, <hi>Prayer,</hi> the beſt comfortable Grace is married to <hi>Hope,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> gives it in marriage, <hi>Faith</hi> is the Prieſt that joyns them together; and the <hi>two Sacraments</hi> are the outward ſigns,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:135920:89"/>
by which they have declared their conſent, as it were, by giving and receiving a Ring, and by joyning of hands.</p>
               <p>Firſt I will treat of <hi>Sacraments</hi> in general, then of each in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar by it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Sacrament being a viſible ſign of inward grace, as a means whereby we receive the ſame, and a pledge to aſſure us thereof;</hi> or more at large, (which comprizeth the end of all ſuch outward ſigns) <hi>a token to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm mens Faith in the promiſes of God:</hi> obſerve firſt, That God hath condeſcended above all expreſſion to our weakneſs, that He would have us to take notice of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in groſs and ſenſible things: A way that is framed to our level, and dull apprehenſion. For <hi>God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:135920:90"/>
him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and Truth, Jo.</hi> 4.24. that's, purely a Heavenly way. But ſome altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been admitted, to bring us forward in our own pace, that is, after humane and bodily fancies. <hi>Deus quandoque inſantilia loquitur.</hi> For our ſakes the Lord ſpeaks in the Scriptures in a plain and vulgar <hi>Emphaſis,</hi> ſtrangely beneath his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite wiſdom, as a nurſe uſeth to babble to her Infant. So He is pleaſed to give himſelf to our hands, to our eyes, to our taſte in common and obvious matter, but out of his ſurpaſſing wiſdom, to make us more ſpiritual, by cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion in a bodily attire.</p>
               <p>The Church began in innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and yet it began with a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>the Tree of life,</hi> inſtituted to keep mankind on Earth immortal by taſting it, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:135920:90"/>
eaten of the Tree of knowledge.</p>
               <p>When the old world was drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and repaired again, God told <hi>Noah,</hi> Gen. 9. <hi>I do ſet my Bow in the cloud, and it ſhall be for a tokken of a Covenant between me and the Earth; that the waters ſhall no more become a floud, to deſtroy all the Earth.</hi> This is the World's Covenant, and not the Churche's, a Covenant to ſave all the Earth from a total deluge. And God is to be perceived, and to be thought of in that ſign, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.28. The glory of the Throne of God was <hi>as the appearance of the Bow that is in the cloud in the day of rain: this was the appearance of the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the glory of the Lord:</hi> and ſo the ſame glory is figur'd in the <hi>Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, Revel.</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <p>After this, it being not diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:135920:91"/>
who did openly and entirely profeſs the worſhip of the true God; <hi>Abraham</hi> was called out of <hi>Chaldea,</hi> and he and his family were imbodied into a Church, and received the ſign of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> as a mark ſtampt upon them, to be known to be thoſe whom God had called out for his own, and did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them to circumciſe the fore-skin of their heart, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.16. Chiefly to imprint into them that the promiſed ſeed ſhould come from that ſtock, in whom all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould be bleſſed.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Abraham's</hi> ſeed became a National Church, before they could get out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the bloud of a <hi>Lamb</hi> was ſprinkled upon their doors, with a ſtatute given upon it, that from thenceforth every fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that time of the year ſhould give account for a Lamb ſlain, and
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:135920:91"/>
be eaten within their houſes, till <hi>John Baptiſt's</hi> Lamb was ſlain to take away the ſin of the world.</p>
               <p>Under the like diſcipline they were trained up for a while in the wilderneſs, when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet up the figure of a <hi>Serpent</hi> upon a Pole, that they might look upon it, and live that were ſtung by Serpents, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. <hi>verſe</hi> 9. The Author of the Book of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> writes Divinely upon it, <hi>That they might be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht for a ſmall ſeaſon it was a ſign of Salvation, — And he that turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf toward it, was not ſaved by the thing he ſaw, but by thee that art the Saviour of the world,</hi> Wiſd. Chap. 16. Verſes 6, 7.</p>
               <p>Neither are we ſuch perfect men under the New Teſtament, to be taught only by the words of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and truth, but we are received
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:135920:92"/>
into the Covenant of Grace, and preſerved in it by Myſteries ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying wonderful things to our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſes, that we may ſuck and be ſatisfied with the Churches <hi>two breaſts of Conſolation, Iſa.</hi> 66.11. And be filled with the <hi>two golden pipes,</hi> that empty the golden oil out of themſelves, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.12.</p>
               <p>I ſtand upon the number of <hi>Two,</hi> becauſe they are put together, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. <hi>The Iſraelites were all baptized in the cloud, did all eat the ſame ſpiritual meat, and all drank of the ſame ſpiritual drink.</hi> As good account for it is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>By one ſpirit we are all baptized into one body, and have been all made to drink into one Spirit.</hi> Or learn it from St. <hi>John</hi> 1 Epiſt. 5.6. <hi>Chriſt came not by water alone, but by water and bloud — And there are three that bear witneſs, the Spirit,</hi> that is,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:135920:92"/>
the miniſtry of the Goſpel; <hi>the water,</hi> that is <hi>Baptiſm; and the bloud,</hi> that is the Lord's Supper. I will not promiſe a preciſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny out of Antiquity, which ſhall ſay there are but two Sacraments under the Goſpel, and no more; but learned men have produced out of the Fathers as much as amounts unto it, to them that will not be contentious. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> 2. <hi>Apol.</hi> to the Emperor ſpeaks of theſe Two marks, or profeſſed ſigns of Chriſtianity, and no other. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> againſt <hi>Marcion, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 51. bring them that are married to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and the Lords Supper. St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. to <hi>Stephen,</hi> Then they are ſanctified, when they are born again by both Sacraments. St. <hi>Cyril</hi> and St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writing purpoſely of Sacraments, ſpeak but of Two. St <hi>Auſtin Ep.</hi> 118. to <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arius,</hi> Chriſt hath ſubjected us to a
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:135920:93"/>
light yoke, to Sacraments of the ſmalleſt number, eaſie in obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, excellent in dignity; Baptiſm in the Name of the Holy Trinity, and the Communion of Chriſts Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Bloud; and if any thing elſe be commanded in Scripture. And many allude to that number from <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Thy breaſts are like two young Roes that are twins.</hi> Here is a brief ſurvey, how God in all Ages hath Communicated with us in Sacraments.</p>
               <p>May the reaſon of it be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? nay, <hi>Who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his Counſellor, Rom.</hi> 11.34. Yet it is no treſpaſs againſt the ſobriety of wiſdom to ask, why Chriſtian Religion depends ſo much upon viſible Sacraments?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, it is to give Faith a third
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:135920:93"/>
manner of corroboration: and a threefold cord is not eaſily broken. Firſt God hath promiſed us all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in Chriſt: Secondly, he gave an Oath for it unto <hi>Abraham; that by two immutable things, in which it was impoſſible for God to lye, we might have a strong conſolation, Heb.</hi> 6.18. Thirdly, after He had plighted both Oath and Promiſe, he hath given us holy Signs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it. When God had both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and ſworn, durſt we of our ſelves have askt a Sign to confirm it, to make us more believing? No truly, we durſt not: for an evil, and an adulterous generation ſeeketh after a Sign: It were a great blemiſh in Faith, if we ſhould appoint God to lend us a crutch to lean upon. But God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented us herein; and, as we ſay in the Common-Prayer, <hi>That which for our unworthineſs we durſt not
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:135920:94"/>
ask,</hi> He hath ſupplied of his own accord, and hath inſtituted Sacred Signs, wrapt up in the Creatures, of moſt ordinary uſe, to make it more eaſie to lay hold of the Hope that is ſet before us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, Every great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in Gods Book, was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſome outward Sign, to make it more comfortable upon ſo remarkable an impreſſion. As <hi>Moſes</hi> being appointed to be the Captain to lead <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> was bade to caſt his Rod before the People, and to let it turn into a Serpent, and return into a Rod again: to make his hand leprous and whole again in an inſtant, by putting it into his boſom, and by drawing it out. And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe Signs in the ſight of the People, and they believed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.31. It would be tedious to recite
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:135920:94"/>
the ſtories of <hi>Aſa, Hezekiah, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſh,</hi> &amp;c. theſe were perſwaded by the Signs of God, that he would viſit them with a mighty delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. But there is no deliverance like unto that, which is brought to paſs for us through the Death and bloudy Paſſion of Chriſt. And the two Sacraments are the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of that great Salvation, which hath ſet us free out of the hands of all our enemies.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, It is meet that great benefits ſhould be faſtned to our memories by a ſure Nail. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, diſtruſting mans memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry repreſents his greateſt works of mercy in the Ordinances of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Signs to prevent forgetfulneſs. The help of ſome outward mark doth avail by experience, to bring that to mind, that elſe would have ſlipt away. As upon occaſion we
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:135920:95"/>
uſe to tye a thred about our fing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or to unlooſe the gemmal of a Ring to make us mindful of a promiſe, or ſome weighty buſineſs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, though all our worſhip muſt hold its tenure, as it were <hi>in capite,</hi> from the Spirit, if we hope to have it acceptable to God, yet we are better capable of ſuch worſhip by the opportunity of material conveyances. Only An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Bleſſed Souls in Heaven can ſerve God in the pure and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material zeal of their mind. But while we are cloathed with fleſh, the mind receives all it takes in from bodily objects: and which paſſeth in by the pipes of the ſenſes, it is connatural to us to apprehend it with mare tenacity and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
               <p>Finally, As Chriſt deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:135920:95"/>
the womb of his Mother, and to walk with us upon Earth; ſo God hath vouchſafed to offer his Word and Promiſe to us in the Creatures of the Earth: ſetting a Seal unto the Word, which makes the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent very valid, and of force and comfort. For if a Commandment of promiſe were remarkable, that of honouring our Parents, the firſt Commandment of promiſe in the ſecond Table, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.2. much more is a Seal and Sacrament of promiſe remarkable. Doubt not then, but as Faith is our hand to receive Chriſt, ſo the Sacraments are, as it were, God's hands to give Him unto us.</p>
               <p>Being paſt the general Survey of viſible Sacraments, it is time to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the conſideration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. Which God hath exalted to marvellous Vertue and Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:135920:96"/>
by his Omnipotent appointment. The <hi>Jews,</hi> that firſt received it, will teach us, that they expected this New and Gracious Ceremony upon the coming of Chriſt. For <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.25. <hi>The Prieſts and Levites ſent to ask</hi> John, <hi>why Baptizeſt thou if thou be not the Chriſt?</hi> &amp;c. It ſeems they had a Tradition, that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ſhould come into the Church with the <hi>Meſſias:</hi> which they learnt, as I take it, from two of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4. ſtates out a famous praiſe of Chriſts Kingdom, then it brings in this, <hi>Verſe</hi> 3. <hi>In that day ſhall the branch of the Lord be beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and glorious — When the Lord ſhall have waſhed away the filth of the daughters of</hi> Sion, <hi>and ſhall have purged the bloud of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>from the midſt thereof.</hi> The other place is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. a plain propheſie of Chriſts Kingdom, and <hi>Verſe</hi> 25. he thus deſcribes it, <hi>Then will I
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:135920:96"/>
ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be cleanſed from all your filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. John</hi> made way unto this Sacrament, and it came from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: therefore the <hi>Phariſees re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the counſel of God, being not Baptized of</hi> John, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. But in the fulneſs of the Goſpel Chriſt confirm'd it. For he that made them promiſe, was the only able perſon to ſet the Seal to ratifie it. Except his admired doctrine, and his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, all things elſe about Chriſt did make no ſhew to outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: ſo he would go no high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the inſtitution of an outward Sign of cleanſing and regeneration, than to bring the people to a River to be waſht, or to a Veſſel of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be ſprinkled. For Faith is drawn through theſe narrow and abject means, that like himſelf have no comelineſs <hi>in ſpecie;</hi> and when we ſee them, there is no comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:135920:97"/>
that we ſhould deſire them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.2.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs it is fit we ſhould be well taught in the Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the hidden vertue incloſed in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or elſe we could never think it worth our labour and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Our Common-Prayer-Book (a ſtore-houſe of rare Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) tells us what is to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at that Laver, for them that come to be Baptized.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God hath promiſed to be the Father of the faithful and of their ſeed, and will moſt ſurely perform, and keep his promiſe with them: and by this introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we are incorporated into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Congregation. Behold, they whom we love above all others by nature, our Children, are naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to be the Citizens of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:135920:97"/>
Kingdom, and enter into it through this door of Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, As God did ſave <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family from periſhing by water, and ſafely led the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> through the Red Sea, while their enemies were drowned: ſo the millions of the Nations whom God hath not given to Chriſt for his inheritance, are drowned in their own luſts and corruptions. But O what a priviledge it is, to be among thoſe few that are received into the Ark of Chriſts Church, to be exempted from the common deluge, and to be the faithful ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> led through the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of the Sea, and Baptized in the Cloud, that went along with them, when the Armies of the mighty are mightily conſumed?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, We may gather out
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:135920:98"/>
of our Church-office for Baptiſm, that the everlaſting benediction of Heavenly waſhing affords two Comforts: it ſignifies the bloud of Chriſt to cleanſe us <hi>Per modum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii,</hi> as the price that was paid to ranſom us from death: and the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying of the Holy Spirit to cleanſe us, <hi>per modum habitûs,</hi> by his In-being, and Celeſtial infuſion; and both are put together in one Collect, <hi>That all that are Baptized may receive remiſſion of ſins by ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual regeneration.</hi> There is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin without bloud, ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. meaning the invaluable bloud of the Lamb of God, <hi>Verſe</hi> 14. And the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly thing is repreſented by the viſible Element of Water: (for there muſt be ſome aptitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sign and the Thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, elſe it were not a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) that as Water waſheth away
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:135920:98"/>
the filth of the body, ſo the Bloud of Chriſt delivereth our Souls from the guilt and damnableneſs of ſin. <hi>The Bloud of Chriſt, his Son, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt. Jo.</hi> 1.7. The metaphor of cleanſing muſt have reſpect to Baptiſmal-water. Again, <hi>Who loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his Bloud, Revel.</hi> 1.5. Where the Scripture ſpeaks of waſhing from ſin, it muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the water of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guring the vertue of Chriſts Bloud, that in the ſight of his Father makes us white as Snow. The Scriptures indeed ſtrike moſt upon the other ſtring, and more directly, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Chriſt loved the Church, and gave himſelf for it, that he might ſanctifie, and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water, by the Word.</hi> Titus 3.6. <hi>He ſaved us by the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of regeneration, and the renewing of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And in many
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:135920:99"/>
other places. Therefore our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy falls moſt upon the <hi>purifying operation of the Spirit,</hi> to be ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the outward waſhing of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. As when it prays, <hi>Send thy Holy Spirit to theſe Infants, and grant that they may be Baptiz'd with Water and with the Holy Ghoſt</hi>— And, <hi>Grant that all that are Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, may receive the fulneſs of thy Grace.</hi> Spiritual Regeneration is that which the Goſpel hath ſet forth to be the principal correlative of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> O happy it is for us to be born again by Water and the Holy Ghoſt! For better it were never to be born, than not to be born twice.</p>
               <p>God put a good mind into us, and reform one great fault in us; which is, that our Baptiſm being paſt over a great while ago, we caſt it out of our memory, and
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:135920:99"/>
meditate but little upon the benefits and comforts of it. We are got into the Church, and do in a ſort forget how we got in. Whereas the whole life of a Chriſtian man and woman ſhould be a continual reflection how in Baptiſm we entred into Covenant with Chriſt, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, to ſerve him, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Devil, the vanities of the world, and the ſinful deſires of the fleſh. <hi>Water</hi> is a pellucid Element to look through it to the bottom: So look often through the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Water, to ſee what Chriſt hath done for you, and what you have engaged to do for Chriſt. And there is no heart ſo full of black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and melancholy, but will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover upon it, and be as freſh in ſound health, as if it were filled with marrow, and fatneſs. Well did St. <hi>Paul</hi> put <hi>Baptiſm</hi> among the principles and foundations of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:135920:100"/>
doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. For all the weight of Faith, Sanctification, and Mercy doth lie upon it. Recount this by particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt thought that my Soul hath upon it is, That I am no longer a ſtranger and foreigner, but a fellow-Citizen with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. I am no more a-far off, but made nigh by the Bloud of Chriſt, partaker of the priviledges of the Church, and called by the new Name, which the mouth of the Lord ſhall name, a Chriſtian, <hi>Iſa. Chap.</hi> 62. <hi>Verſe</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, I find that I have gained to have the higheſt point of Faith unfolded to me, which was but darkly diſcerned in the Old Teſtament, to confeſs the Holy Trinity, in which Faith I was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:135920:100"/>
For becauſe that myſtery was revealed at Chriſts Baptiſm, it goes ever along with this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All Nations being Baptized in the Name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, I obſerve that my Chriſtian engagement allows me not the liberty of ſinning after the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the world; but obligeth me to the ſtrict diſcipline of my Lord, to live holily, juſtly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, to walk in newneſs of life, as planted into the likeneſs of Chriſts death, ſo to die unto ſin: for <hi>he that is dead, is freed from ſin, Rom.</hi> 6.7. In every thing, and at all times I muſt remember what the Sureties at the Font, called God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for me in my Name; which the Liturgy of <hi>Geneva</hi> retains in theſe words, <hi>Do you promiſe to warn
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:135920:101"/>
this Child to live according to God's Word, and make the Law of God the ſquare of his life to live by?</hi> 'Tis a binding Ceremony, and we are brought up from our tender years in the knowledge of it, that we continually may feel the work of the Ordinance, to have our hearts ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, and our bodies waſht with clean Water, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.21, 22. And <hi>as many as are Baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3.27. To put on Chriſt is to follow Chriſt in the Law of a new Creature, and to perfect holineſs; without which no man ſhall ſee God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, I have aſſurance that the Spirit is not disjoyned from the Water: for Chriſts Word can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſail, that we ſhall be Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>But ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:135920:101"/>
are juſtified in the Name of the Lord</hi> Jeſus, <hi>and by the Spirit of our God,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. The power given to keep the Covenant makes it a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace: elſe we ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter but the Letter, and not the Spirit. The outward act of man, unleſs we make our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, is certainly aſſiſted with the increaſe of God. If the good effect enſue not, the Sacrament doth not want its vertue, but the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver marr'd it. Very much its to be aſcribed to the Word preacht: it is a powerful means to convert us, and to ſave us. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Take heed unto thy doctrine, for in doing this thou ſhalt ſave thy ſelf, and them that hear thee.</hi> And 1 Pet. 1.23. <hi>Being born again not of corruptible ſeed, but incorruptible, by the Word of God, which liveth and abideth in you.</hi> The Word diſpoſeth, and prepares: God is the efficient cauſe
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:135920:102"/>
of our Regeneration. Now this Sacrament, whether we ſpeak of Infants, they are to call to mind how they received the outward Seal of Grace; or whether we ſpeak of Converts of ripe years, who at the ſame time were taught the vertue of it, it hath reaſon to work more powerfully and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon their knowledge and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than doctrine alone: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt and his Benefits are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in a ſenſible operation, which himſelf did dignifie in his own perſon at the waters of <hi>Jordan,</hi> and afterward inſtitute it to be uſed by all his Diſciples.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth thing that I draw from hence gives me exceeding Conſolation in Chriſt, that no man who is made the Child of God is in the damnable ſtate of ſin; therefore in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> being made the adopted
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:135920:102"/>
Child of God, I have obtained the pardon of all ſins, Original and Actual: as <hi>Naaman</hi> was cured of all his leproſie. <hi>Who ſaved us by the waſhing of Regeneration,</hi> Tit. 3.6. <hi>Be Baptized every one of you, in the Name of the Lord</hi> Jeſus, <hi>for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins,</hi> Acts 2.38: So <hi>Ananias</hi> ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 22.16. <hi>Ariſe, and be Baptized, and waſh away thy ſins.</hi> Yea, but ſome will cavil, Infants have not Faith; and God hath ſet forth Chriſt to be a propitiation through Faith in his Bloud: and he that believeth and is Baptized, ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. I will not contend about it, whether Baptized Infants have a ſecret imperceptible habit of Faith: I am ſure there is Innocency of life in them inſtead of Faith. They that are of Age to come to the knowledge of Faith, muſt bring their own Faith with them to the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:135920:103"/>
Font: but for Infants, they have priviledge to be in Church-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by the Faith of the Church, wherein they were born. There is another conteſt made by ſome, that, notwithſtanding Baptiſm, Original ſin remains in us all the days of our life. True: the ſin is not blotted out in the Infant, but it is blotted out of the Book of God. And as Actual ſins are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd for Chriſt's ſake, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be brought about that they ſhould never be done, which are done and paſt, but it is enough that they ſhall not be imputed: ſo Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ſin cleaves unto us, it is not caſt out, for I feel it in me; but it is remitted.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For the complement of this ſubject, the largeſt and the longeſt Comfort flowing from the Grace of Baptiſm is, That we are to rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:135920:103"/>
the Covenant, made between God and us therein, for the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all our ſins, which we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit after Baptiſm unto the end of our life. Far be it from me to ſay, that it ſufficeth us to caſt our eyes back to the Covenant then made, as if the bare and hiſtorical memory of it did ſuffice to blot out ſins; that's but an empty flaſh, and a vapour of preſumption. But this I ſay, Build upon the Eternity and Infallibility of God's Truth: and then by a true and ſure-graſping Faith, joyn'd with Repentance, renew your ſelf in God's mercies by the promiſe of the Old Baptiſmal Covenant. Repentance is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition never to be omitted to lift us up again, when we have been overtaken with ſins. But Faith doth not comfort it ſelf in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of Repentance, which in us is ever imperfect, but in Chriſt's
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:135920:104"/>
merits once for all conſigned to us in Baptiſm. For the Scriptures ſpeak indefinitely, that the Laver of Regeneration purgeth away all our ſins; it doth not ſpeak reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively of ſins paſt, as if it did ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate no longer than in that moment, when the water is ſprinkled. For Baptiſm doth now, at the very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time ſave us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. And ſome collect it out of that figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive place, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 49.9. <hi>Every thing where the Waters do come, ſhall live.</hi> After a ſhower of rain is fallen, and ceaſeth, the graſs continues to grow. By grievous and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ſins we debar our ſelves from the ſenſe, and comfort of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for the preſent: yet when we repent, we come not to make a new Covenant with God, but to beſeech him to be gracious to us for the old Covenants ſake. As an Adultereſs, if ſhe be received again,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:135920:104"/>
and pardon'd by her Husband, is not new married, but accepted for a wife upon the firſt contract of marriage.</p>
               <p>Take ſome examples of thoſe in the New Teſtament, that ſinned againſt God, and in their return again, did not ſuppoſe the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Baptiſm to be aboliſht, but they comforted themſelves that the mercies promiſed then would hold firm, and not fail them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> challengeth the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. that they had been Adulterers, Effeminate, and much of the like. Yet <hi>Verſe</hi> 11. he ſpeaks thus to them, <hi>Ye are waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſanctified, juſtified in the Name of the Lord</hi> Jeſus. In the ſame manner he deals with the <hi>Galatians,</hi> who had embraced much falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, mingled <hi>Judaiſm</hi> with the Goſpel; yet <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Verſe</hi> 27.
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:135920:105"/>
                  <hi>As many of you as are Baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</hi> Can any thing equal all theſe heart-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhings that ſwim in the pool of Baptiſm? Therefore in many Ages paſt, the joy of the <hi>Neophytes</hi> was exceſſive that came to be Baptized. Many Torches were lighted, and carried before them; to ſhew it was the day of their illumination. They came in white garments, and wore them conſtantly eight days together, a moſt Feſtival habit. Yet they affected too much to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their Baptiſm till their elder, nay their lateſt years, out of the erroneous principle, that Baptiſm was the healing water for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins paſt: and they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther relied upon Repentance, than upon the Baptiſm, which they had received, for the remiſſion of ſins that did follow. Whereas Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is not a new paction with
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:135920:105"/>
God, but a return to the uſe of the old: a reſtitution as it were to our bloud, when we had been tainted by committing Treaſon againſt God; that is, repoſſeſſion of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endanger'd to be forfeited. But were it a new Covenant, we ſhould have ſome new viſible Sign for it, which never was. Therefore this is the very Soul of mine and every ones Baptiſmal Conſolation, that being once done, it Seals pardon for all our ſins through Chriſts bloud unto our lifes end.</p>
               <p>BUT as if many Spouts ſhould open into one Ciſtern, ſo all Comforts conſpire to meet in the Sacrament of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> Nothing elſe but the actual enjoying of Heaven is above it. The Church, which diſpenſeth all the myſteries of ſalvation, can bring
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:135920:106"/>
forth no better. Children that are come to Age, can ask no more than the whole portion of their Father's goods that come unto them: and what is that but the Bloud of Chriſt? and this is <hi>the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that Bloud.</hi> Chriſt is mine, his Body is mine, his Bloud is mine, all is mine. <hi>O be glad and rejoyce, and give honour to the Lord God Omnipotent, for the marriage of the Lamb is come,</hi> Revel. 19.7. And the Spirit ſaith, write, <hi>Bleſſed are they that are called to the marriage-ſupper of the Lamb,</hi> Verſe 9. It is much to be received into a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God by the former Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: is it not more to be kept in Covenant by the other? It is much in Baptiſm to be brought from death to life: but what is life without nouriſhment to preſerve it? This keeps us in the Leaſe of the old Covenant, that the Years
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:135920:106"/>
of it ſhall never run out, and expire. This is food to keep us in health and ſtrength, that we never decay and faint. By it we lay hold of the promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>My kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the Covenant of my peace be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, ſaith the Lord that hath mercy on thee.</hi> Then why ſhould I not embolden my heart with holy ſecurity againſt all fears; for the Lord hath put himſelf into my hand, and into my mouth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Spirit: of what then ſhould I be afraid? This is that courage which our Liturgy ſounds forth, as with a ſhrill Trumpet, to all that come to this Banquet well prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: It begins, that it is a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thing to all them that receive it worthily; it bids us come with a full truſt in Gods mercy, and with a quiet Conſcience: it proclaims aloud, Hear what comfortable
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:135920:107"/>
words our Saviour Chriſt ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that truly come unto him, <hi>So God loved the world,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me all ye,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This is a true ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c. It hath gathered the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of ſpiritual joy, as it were, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a bundle of Myrrhe. It adds, <hi>Chriſt hath inſtituted and ordained holy myſteries, as pledges of his love, and for a continual remembrance of his death, to our great and endleſs comfort.</hi> And if all this put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not blandiſh our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſtabliſh our joy, we would be dull and ſpirit-broken, though an Angel from Heaven ſhould come and ſay unto us, as he did unto <hi>Gideon, The Lord is with thee, thou mighty man of valour, Jud.</hi> 6.12. For an Angel of the Lord cannot plead ſo much to the ſolace of the heart, as the great Angel of the Covenant hath done in theſe great demonſtrations of love, as followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:135920:107"/>1. Firſt, As Baptiſm was the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſo this is the ſecond viſible publication of God's apparent mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. It is not a bare meſſage, but a lively apprehenſion of them by pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable means: not in a viſion, or a dream, but in a real Object. Call to mind that the Lord was angry with <hi>Solomon,</hi> becauſe his heart was turned from the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had appeared unto him <hi>twice,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.39. <hi>Once</hi> the Lord hath appeared unto us in the token of his love by <hi>Water:</hi> and <hi>once again</hi> he appears unto us in the Elements of his <hi>Holy Table. Twice</hi> he hath appeared to bleſs thee. Therefore <hi>eat thy Bread with joy, and drink thy Wine with a merry heart, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.7. For if you turn away from Comfort, when the Lord hath appeared <hi>twice</hi> unto you to give it you, he will be angry, and leave you to a thick darkneſs
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:135920:108"/>
of ſorrow, ſuch as fell upon the land of <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, The Lord can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Comfortably unto us, though with a Sword in his hand, and in the midſt of a Camp, as he did to <hi>Joſuah, Joſ.</hi> 5.13. Or in a flame of fire, as he did to <hi>Manoah, Jud.</hi> 13.20. Or in a tempeſt upon the Sea, as he did to the Apoſtles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.27. Or at the Graves mouth, as he did to <hi>Mary Magdalen, Jo.</hi> 20.14. But here he appears unto us in a Feaſt, which is a time of innocent delight. The glory of God, which we look for, is ſet out unto us in that which our ſenſes apprehend for ſweetneſs and pleaſure: as <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29. <hi>I appoint unto you a Kingdom — that ye may Eat and Drink at my Table in my Kingdom:</hi> which is tranſlated from bodily pleaſure to ſpiritual, that in the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:135920:108"/>
Heaven of bleſſedneſs the Soul ſhall feed continually as at a Banquet: of which we have now a taſte in the Kingly proviſion of Chriſts Supper. It is <hi>a Kingly Feaſt,</hi> although im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in a little pittance of Bread and Wine: yet it is more coſtly and precious to that which it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, than <hi>Solomon</hi> and all his Court had for their diet day by day, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.22. We are brought to Eat at the King's Table, as <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> was, like one of the Kings Sons, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.11. To Eat together is a Communion of more than ordinary acquaintance: do you note the endearing favour of God in that? And what are we, that are not thruſt, as our kind might look for it, to gather up Crums under the Board, but to Eat our portion before the Lord, with the Lord, out of the hands of the Lord? For he that brake Bread,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:135920:109"/>
and gave it to the Apoſtles, gives it to Us, as our High Prieſt, though he be in Heaven. I exhort you therefore to enter into the Gueſt-chamber with a quiet, and unſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart: for the Lord hath not invited us as <hi>Abſalom</hi> did <hi>Amnon,</hi> to kill us: nor as <hi>Eſther</hi> did <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> to accuſe us; but as <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech</hi> brought forth Bread and Wine to <hi>Abraham</hi> to bleſs us. He gives us <hi>Aſher's</hi> portion, Bread that ſhall be fat, and Royal dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.20. Only the caſe is alter'd, if Chriſt ſhall ſay, the hand of him that betrays me, the hand of him that loves me not, the hand of him that believes not in me, the hand of him that will not keep my ſayings, is on the Table. That wretch ſhall be thrown out, and be fed with Bread of ſorrow, and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of affliction, nay, where there ſhall not be a drop of Water to cool his Tongue.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:135920:109"/>Thirdly, That which aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the Communicant, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſheth his heart is, that this Feaſt affords no worſe meat than the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Bloud of our Saviour. Thoſe he gave for the life of the world, theſe are the repaſt of this Supper, and theſe we truly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take. For there is not only the viſible reception of the outward Signs, but an inviſible reception of the thing ſignified. There is far more than a ſhadow, than a type, than a figure. Chriſt did not only propoſe a Sign at that hour, but alſo he gave us a Gift, and that Gift really and effectually is Himſelf, which is all one as you would ſay, Spiritually himſelf: for <hi>Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is the moſt true, and real union that can be. That which is promiſed, and Faith takes it, and hath it, is not fiction, fanſie, opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:135920:110"/>
falſity, but ſubſtance and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Being ſtrengthened with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer by the Spirit in the inward mind, Chriſt dwelleth in our hearts by Faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. As by a Ring, or a meaner inſtrument of conveyance, a man may be ſetled in Land, or put into an Office: and by ſuch conveyances the Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of ſuch Grants are held to be real. How much more real is the gift and receipt of Chriſt's Body and Bloud, when conveyed unto us by the confirmation of the Eternal Spirit? For obſerve, it is the ſame Spirit that is in Chriſt, and that is in Us, and we are quickned by one and the ſame Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. Therefore it cannot chuſe, but that a real Union muſt follow between Chriſt and Us: as there is a Union between all the parts of a Body, by the animation of one Soul. But Faith is the mouth wherewith we
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:135920:110"/>
Eat his Body, and Drink his Bloud; not the mouth of a man, but of a Faithful man: for we hunger after him, not with a Corporal appetite, but a Spiritual; therefore our Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt be Spiritual, and not Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. Yet this is a real, a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial partaking of Chriſt crucified, broken, his fleſh bleeding, his wounds gaping: ſo he is exhibited, ſo we are ſure we receive him, which doth not only touch our outward ſenſes in the Elements, but paſs through into the depth of the Soul. For in true Divinity <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> are aequipollent: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though with the <hi>Papiſts</hi> nothing is <hi>real</hi> unleſs it be <hi>corporal:</hi> which is a groſs way, to defraud us of the Sublime and Soul-raviſhing vertue of the myſtery. A myſtery nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſet out in words, nor to be comprehended ſufficiently in the mind, but to be adored with Faith,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:135920:111"/>
ſays <hi>Calvin, lib. Inſtit. c.</hi> 17. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. But herein we pledge Chriſt in the Cup of love, herein we renew the Covenant of forgiveneſs ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſured by the ſprinkling of Bloud: the life is in the Bloud: and without ſhedding of Bloud is no remiſſion of ſins. Becauſe death is the wages of ſin. Sin is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſhonour that can be done to God: and death in Chriſt's perſon is the greateſt ſatisfaction that can be made. He died, and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for me: he died and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to me, as he was dead in his gored and pierced body, that his ſacrifice might be in me, and in all thoſe that are redeemed by it. We read of ſome Mothers, that in a great famine have eaten their own Children, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. but what Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the time of famine did ever give her own fleſh to ſave the life of her Child? But Chriſt hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:135920:111"/>
himſelf for us, that we might not periſh. <q>O Lord, I owe all my life to thee, becauſe thou haſt laid down thy life for me. O let me bleed out my ſins, that thy Bloud may fill all the veins of my Spirit. O let my Body be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figur'd to be Heavenly by clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and chaſtity, by being uſed only for thy worſhip and ſervice, that the Body of my Saviour may come under the roof of it. Then when the King ſhall let forth his Table, and give himſelf to me in his wonderful Feaſt, my Spick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard ſhall ſend forth a ſweet ſmell, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.12. <hi>My Soul ſhall magnifie the Lord, and my Spirit ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in Chriſt my Saviour.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We have found the Meſſias,</hi> ſays <hi>Philip</hi> to <hi>Nathaniel:</hi> And where have we found him? at a Feaſt: a Feaſt of his own Body and Bloud,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:135920:112"/>
but ſet out with no more coſt and ſhew than a piece of Bread, and a ſip of Wine. In this manner it is brought to paſs by the Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God's pleaſure to inſtitute it, with the efficacy of a ſtrong Faith concurring to receive it. The Church had done very ill, if of its own head it had made ſo mean a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of Chriſt: but the Lord muſt be obeyed, and ought to be admired in the humility of his Ordinance, who hath not given us rich Viands, and full Cups, but made the Feaſt out of the fragments of the meaneſt Creatures. Let them underſtand this that will make themſelves fit to be his gueſts, bring a preparation of humility ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the exility of thoſe oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>The meek ſhall Eat and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, they ſhall praiſe the Lord and ſeek him, Pſalm</hi> 22.26. And at that ſeaſon let the riotous remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:135920:112"/>
his fulneſs of Bread, and exceſs of Wine. God is honour'd in a little, and his liberality is abuſed in the exceſs of his creatures. And it is worth the noting, that the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which we are invited to take, are of fruits that grow out of the Earth; to ſhew that the Earth, which was curſed for <hi>Adam's</hi> ſake, is bleſſed for Chriſt's ſake. As it brings forth Thorns and Thiſtles to call to mind our rebellion, ſo it brings forth Bread and Wine to call to mind our redemption. Neither doth God ſupply us with Bread on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the furrows of the Earth, but ſometime it hath fallen out of the clouds of Heaven. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſays God, <hi>I will rain Bread from Heaven for you, Exod.</hi> 16.4. This was <hi>Manna,</hi> called <hi>the Corn of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Pſalm</hi> 78.24. This was the Spiritual meat, or Angels food, in which the old believers in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:135920:113"/>
did Eat Chriſt with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Faith. Our outward Sign is the Bread of the Earth, true Bread that grows in the Fields, yet the Bread ſignified is that which the Father hath given us from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.31. Bread is a great part of mans nouriſhment; ſo Chriſt crucified is the ſole refection of Faith. Bread is champed in the mouth to make it fit for the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach: ſo the Body of Chriſt was ordained to be ſlain, before it could profit us. <hi>If the Corn of Wheat fall not into the ground and die, it abideth alone; but if it die, it bringeth ſorth much fruit,</hi> Jo. 12.24. By his life we learn to live, and by his death we are made alive. Bread when it is grounded between our teeth, and eaten, is turn'd by concoction into the ſubſtance of our Body: which explains our myſtical union with Chriſt, that we
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:135920:113"/>
are made one Spirit with him by Faith, as this ſenſible food is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into our fleſh and bone.</p>
               <p>Beſide, in the ſeveral parts of the outward Signs, it is God's meaning we ſhould conceive how he loves the gathering together of many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one: which is thus to be qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. At a common Supper, or any Meal, all that are at the Board feed of the ſame Meats; yet every one feeds to himſelf, and to none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide: So every Communicant Eats Chriſt to himſelf, and the juſt ſhall live by his own Faith. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it is a Sacrament to combine, and to knit together, holding us faſt into one Communion, that there may be no breaking aſunder of the parts and members. Many grains of Wheat are kneaded into one Loaf, many Grapes are trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, that their liquor may be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:135920:114"/>
into one cup. <hi>We being many are one Bread, and one Body: for we are all partakers of that one Bread,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. Now natural learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will teach us, what a Comfort there is in Union, and that fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diſſolutions are painful and grievous. Behold, how good and pleaſant a thing it is! behold, what a ſtrengthening to the myſtical Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to continue in one fellowſhip and breaking of Bread, to link Faith and Love together in <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt! It was but one deliverance common to all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was kept at the Paſſeover, though every Lamb was Eaten by it ſelf in a ſeveral family: So it is one Cup of ſalvation which God hath given us to Drink, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to the faithful according to the multitude of perſons: and it is one Bread of which all do Eat, though ſome have one ſhare of it,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:135920:114"/>
and ſome another. It is neceſſary that many pieces be broken off from one Loaf, to typifie the Body of the Lord broken for us, and that the benefits of his Paſſion are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed among us.</p>
               <p>There are many inſtances that are pregnant to prove, how pieces of ſomething broken, and divided into many ſhares do import a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of ſomewhat among the dividers. The Heathen, at the making of a League, did now and then break a Flint-ſtone into pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and they that entred into a League kept the parts in token of a Covenant. Some upon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of marriage will break a piece of Gold, and the two halfs are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the contractors. Shall I go further, and yet come nearer to our caſe? The <hi>Roman</hi> Souldiers parted our Saviour's garment
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:135920:115"/>
among them, and in that Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal accident is ſhewn, that the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> ſhould ſhare in the ſatisfaction of his death. So <hi>Peter</hi> takes this morſel of the Bread, <hi>John</hi> another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet Chriſt is not divided. The ſame Ticket, as it were, in words in ſubſtance is put into every hand, on which is written, <hi>Take and Eat it in remembrance of me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take it,</hi> ſays Chriſt, and be not afraid, as <hi>Saul</hi> was, to take a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſince Chriſt hath appointed it: be not afraid, as <hi>David</hi> was, to be the Kings Son, ſince ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is predeſtinated to thee. Take it, and fear not, as <hi>Peter</hi> did, ſaying, <hi>Depart from me, Lord, for I am a ſinful man;</hi> it is the Lord's delight to ſeek and to ſave that which is loſt. Take it, and take heed you let not go your hold; the thing is faſt and firm, if you do
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:135920:115"/>
not let it go, and loſe it. Take it, but not to hold the pleaſures of the world, and your ſinful luſts in your gripe together: if your hands be full of thoſe things, you can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hold this. Take it, and take Chriſt with it: for He that made the Teſtament in his Bloud, hath ſet the Seal unto the Teſtament, which gives you interefs and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Redemption by his Bloud. Take it, and reach out your hand, to ſignifie that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt with the hand of Faith. They are too nice, for fear of I know not what in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, of loſing a crum, or ſo forth, that they put the Body of Chriſt into the mouth of their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: and in pretence that they give it as a Mother doth her breaſt into the mouth of her Child: whereas we receive this Sacrament, not as Babes, but as thoſe that are
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:135920:116"/>
grown to the meaſure of a good Age. And if we be not worthy to take it into our hands, we are not worthy to receive it in our mouth. Take it, and eat it: for it is not enough to be ſprinkled without, but to feed on Chriſt, and to digeſt him within. If upon the ſupply of Corn, and Beaſts, and Cattel, <hi>Paul</hi> might ſay, that <hi>God had filled our hearts with food and gladneſs,</hi> Acts 14.17. If we are glad of that which ſuſtains us for a time, and yet we muſt die: How glad will we be to Eat of that, as will give us ſuch a life, that will endure for ever? Eat of the forbidden Tree, ſays the Serpent to <hi>Eve,</hi> and you ſhall not die; but he lied unto her. Therefore to diſſolve the works of the Devil, our Saviour hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that which we ſhall Eat, and aſſured the promiſe of Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life unto it. Eat as <hi>Jonathan</hi>
                  <pb n="211" facs="tcp:135920:116"/>
did of th Hony-comb, that you may be luſty to purſue your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and though Satan hath ſworn your death, as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan's,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.44. the Lord will deliver you. Pine not away with the conſumption of an evil Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but Eat, and be ſtrong in the Lord, and in his mercy. As the Spirit of the <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> who was half dead, came to him again, when he had Eaten a little, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.12. Eat, and grind the Bread between your teeth, to ſhew the Lord's death. For Chriſt could have ſaid, <hi>This is my Body ſlain, This is my Body crucified,</hi> but he had rather ſay, <hi>This is my Body bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for you,</hi> to ſhew the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries of his ſufferings. Eat then, and remember you Eat the Body as it was broken, and remember that you Drink the blood as it flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his wounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:135920:117"/>To keep theſe things in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance is the great deſign of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: an object which keeps the fancy of the Soul waking, that otherwiſe, it may be, would fall aſleep. In the ſixth of St. <hi>John</hi> Chriſt Preacheth over and over of <hi>Eating his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Drinking his Bloud</hi> without a Sacrament, by the power of Faith. But to keep it in freſh and frequent meditation, the Lord hath given us a palpable and ſignal token, as if he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave it upon the palms of our hands, and upon the roof of our mouth, upon the membranes of our brain, and upon the foreskin of our heart. This is a bleſſing twice, and twenty times given, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is given that it may never be forgotten. They that love others, would live in the memory of thoſe they love: it is becauſe
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:135920:117"/>
Chriſt loves us entirely, that he would be remembred of us. And no friend will ſay to another, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me when I am gone, but that he means reciprocally to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his friend, to whom he ſpake it. If you will remember Chriſt, he will remember you. And the Thief on the Croſs will teach you, that it is good to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in his memory; <hi>Lord, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me when thou com'ſt into thy Kingdom.</hi> O bleſſed Chriſt! thou art good, and doſt good: thou haſt not only provided an invalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able benefit for thy Church, but doſt put it into our hands, that we may not loſe it; and doſt bring it into our eyes by clear oſtenſion, that we may not forget it. We are apt to remember injuries, and to forget benefits: unthankfulneſs will undo us, if we take not heed of
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:135920:118"/>
it. O rub over your memory, and conſider the noble works of the Lord, eſpecially this great work, how he ſuffered for us unto Death. Remember ſeriouſly this one thing as you ought, and God will let you forget nothing that will do you good. There is no grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſin which we incur, but for the preſent Chriſt is forgotten, as if he had never come to charge us to keep our ſelves unſpotted from the world. But look upon his wounds which bleed for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and it will ſtanch the flux of ſin, and make our hearts bleed, becauſe we have forgotten obedience. In our diſtreſſes, our ſickneſs, and loſſes, we cry out that God hath forgotten us, he hath forgotten to be gracious, and ſhuts up his loving kindneſs in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. But diſtruſt him not:
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:135920:118"/>
a Mother cannot forget her Child: much-leſs ſuch a Father. Every tribulation which he inflicts, is but a Thorn in our ſides to prick us, and awake us, becauſe we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten God.</p>
               <p>And remember the Death of Chriſt, not only caſting your eyes back to the large Hiſtories of it in the Goſpels, as if that would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: but affectingly, practically, zealouſly: and then every thing elſe will come to mind to perfect holineſs. When we remember his Death, we are ſure he is paſt Death, and Riſen again, now to Die no more, and that he is Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Heaven, and makes Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us. We have obtained that Faith that we partake in the New Teſtament of his Bloud, and that our Names being found in the
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:135920:119"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="217" facs="tcp:135920:119"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:135920:120"/>
Teſtament, we are heirs of God, co-heirs with Chriſt. The cuſtom of the world will teach us, that an Heir is bound to execute the Will of the Teſtator, to ſee every thing perform'd that he hath charg'd and bequeathed. Do your part like a true Executor, with a righteous Adminiſtration in remembrance of him. But forgetfulneſs cannot creep upon us, when there is ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible a Monument before us to bring it often into our thoughts. <hi>Luther</hi> ſays, it will help a man more in the ſtudy of Piety, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate profoundly upon Chriſt's Paſſion one day, than to read over all the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David.</hi> A bold compariſon: It will indeed raviſh the Soul with trembling, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how much Chriſt loved us, by how much he ſuffered for us: it will make us look upon ſin with
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:135920:120"/>
horror, which begat ſuch torment and ignominy to the innocent Lamb of God: it will Comfort our weak Faith, that he who hath done ſo great things for us, will not abandon us; and having ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Enemies, will not let them renew the Battel to overcome us: it will encourage us to lay down our life for him, who hath laid down his life for us. <hi>My medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him ſhall be ſweet, I will be glad in the Lord, Pſalm</hi> 104.34. He hath drunk up the Cup of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that I might drink of nothing but the Cup of Salvation. This is the Wine, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.6. which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given unto him that hath a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy heart, confutes all the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Infidelity, Deſpair, an evil Conſcience, or whatſoever the tempter can ſuggeſt againſt the Hope of my Glorifications. Says
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:135920:121"/>
the Son of <hi>Syrach,</hi> Chap. 49.1. <hi>The remembrance of</hi> Joſias <hi>was ſweet as Hony in all mouths, and as Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick at a Banquet of Wine.</hi> If the Name of <hi>Joſias</hi> was ſo precious for reſtoring Religion, what melody is there in the remembrance of Chriſt's Name, what Muſick in his Banquet, which is the very Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-ſeat, from whence the voice of the Lord gives the principal Oracles of <hi>Conſolation?</hi> Whoſe Definition I have reſerved to be the laſt words of all; <hi>Conſolatio eſt conveniens <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nio potentiae cum Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto,</hi> as our beſt Scholars have it; <hi>Conſolation is a convenient <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of any Faculty with its Object.</hi> As when the Eye meets with light, it is the Comfort of the Eye. When the Ear meets with harmony, it is the Comfort of the Ear. What is the moſt tranſcendent Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:135920:121"/>
therefore, but the Union of the Soul with God, the beſt Object, in a real and moſt ſignificative manner, the Union of the Spirit with Chriſt in the Sacrament of his Holy Supper. To whom be Praiſe, and Glory, and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 39. line 21. read <hi>taught us:</hi> p. 54. l. 18. r. <hi>theſe:</hi> p. 59. l. 18. r. <hi>wherefore:</hi> p. 146. l. 5. r. <hi>God that:</hi> p. 187. in the Title, read <hi>the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:135920:122"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> ſince the Fire.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Paraphraſe and Annotations upon all the Books of the New Teſtament. The third Edition: by <hi>H. Hammond, D. D.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ductor Dubitantium,</hi> Or the Rule of Conſcience, in Four Books, Folio. The ſecond Edition: by <hi>Jer. Taylor,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Conner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Sinner Impleaded in his own Court: The third Edition: Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is now added, The love of Chriſt planted upon the very ſame Turf, on which it once had been Supplanted by the extream Love of Sin: in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Collection of Sermons upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral occaſions: by <hi>Tho. Pierce, D.D.</hi> and Preſident of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi>-Colledge in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:135920:122"/>A Diſcourſe concerning the true Notion of the Lords Supper, to which are added two Sermons: by <hi>R. Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, D. D.</hi> in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> requiring our Communion with the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi>-Church: in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
